<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Zingis a Tartarian history / written in Spanish ; and translated into English by J.M. ...</title>
            <title>Zingis. English</title>
            <author>La Roche-Guilhen, Mlle de (Anne), 1644-1707.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 195 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 91 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49596</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9927</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12148167</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12148167</idno>
            <idno type="VID">55009</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49596)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 55009)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 109:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Zingis a Tartarian history / written in Spanish ; and translated into English by J.M. ...</title>
                  <title>Zingis. English</title>
                  <author>La Roche-Guilhen, Mlle de (Anne), 1644-1707.</author>
                  <author>J. M.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 176 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Francis Saunders ... and Richard Parker ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Mlle. de LaRoche-Guihen. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. 176.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Yale University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:55009:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55009:1"/>
            <p>ZINGIS: A Tartarian Hiſtory. WRITTEN In <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> and Tranſlated into <hi>ENGLISH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>J. M.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Humbly Dedicated to the EARL of <hi>DALKEITH,</hi> Apparent Duke of <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Francis Saunders</hi> in the <hi>New Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change,</hi> and <hi>Richard Parker</hi> at the <hi>Royal Exchange,</hi> 1692.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:55009:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:55009:2"/>
            <head>TO THE Right Honourable LORD JOHN, EARL of <hi>DALKEITH,</hi> Apparent DUKE of <hi>B<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>CCL<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>GH.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>AMong the many <hi>Ornaments</hi> which <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune</hi> hath beſtowed, <hi>Nature</hi> infuſed, or <hi>Noble Induſtry</hi> acquired to your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, there is none more Illuſtrious than your <hi>Love</hi> to your <hi>Country,</hi> generous <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy,</hi> and courteous <hi>Facility</hi> to all Men: And indeed as theſe Noble Virtues always moſt flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhingly budded in the early Blooms of your Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's tender Years, ſo they do now moſt ripely and radiantly diſplay themſelves in the glorious Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhine of your couragious Inclinations and honour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Intentions; Which alſo as they do encourage
<pb facs="tcp:55009:3"/>an obſcure Stranger (deſiring to grace his weak <hi>Endeavours</hi> with the Honour of your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip's Name</hi> prefix'd) to proſtrate this <hi>ſmall Piece</hi> at your Lordſhip's Feet; ſo they do juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly entitle your Lordſhip to the Nobleſt Actions of the greateſt <hi>Heroes,</hi> and incline you to grant your <hi>Patronage</hi> to the unworthieſt of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhip's moſt humble and devoted Servants, <hi>J. M.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:55009:3"/>
            <head>ZINGIS: A Tartarian Hiſtory.</head>
            <p>EAſtern <hi>Tartary,</hi> after having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy'd ſeveral Kings worthy to govern that fair Canton of the World, ſaw her ſelf in the end ſubje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to <hi>Undkan</hi> a weak Prince, and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd by an imperious Wife, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpir'd him only with violent Reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. The City of <hi>Cambalu,</hi> where the Kings ordinarily reſided, every way magnificent and glorious in the Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty of ſix Kings who ſtay'd at <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Court, was upon the point of being made a Theatre of the Cruelty of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:55009:4"/>
               <hi>Zamar,</hi> for ſo was the Wife of that Prince called.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Undkan</hi> had an only Daughter of his firſt Marriage, call'd <hi>Taxila,</hi> who was admir'd by all the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and whom he deſign'd for the Son of the Queen his Wife. That Prince, nam'd <hi>Timur,</hi> was King of <hi>Tenduc,</hi> and in lieu of all merit had the blind love of an ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Mother, capable of ſacrificing all things to her own Grandeur.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs of <hi>Tartary</hi> was born with admirable perfections, never was there ſeen any thing ſo fair as ſhe. The Charms of her Wit equall'd thoſe of her Beauty. She had a great Soul, a perfect Virtue, and it may be ſaid that Heaven was not wanting in its Favours to her. Her Inclinations were very op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the deſigns of the King her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and in ſpite of <hi>Timur</hi>'s pretenſions, ſhe avoided dexterouſly the force of the abſolute Orders that were impos'd upon
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:55009:4"/>her. But her Heart, which the Son of <hi>Zamar</hi> could not touch, was neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs not inſenſible. <hi>Zingis</hi> who was baniſh'd from <hi>Cambalu,</hi> tho' guilty of no Crime, but that of having too much merit, occaſion'd a tender unquietneſs in her Soul. She ſaw all leagu'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, <hi>Undkan, Zamar, Timur,</hi> and ſeveral Kings, cowardly adorers of a Tyrannick Power. <hi>Taxila</hi> alone took his part, with a perſeverance due unto the ſervices of that illuſtrious Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver: but he was abſent, and the jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous <hi>Timur</hi> poſſeſs'd of an abſolute Power by the Authority of his unjuſt Mother.</p>
            <p>One night <hi>Taxila</hi> wholly taken up with the remembrance of <hi>Zingis,</hi> heard a great noiſe, and ſaw the King her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther enter into her Chamber, who came, with eyes full of fury, to upbraid her with holding private Intelligence with his moſt mortal enemy. After an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:55009:5"/>number of injurious Speeches, he commanded her to be ſtrictly guarded in her apartments, where he left her alone.</p>
            <p>The Princeſs eaſily judg'd that this Enemy he talk'd of could be no other but <hi>Zingis;</hi> but ſhe could not compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend what had mov'd <hi>Undkan,</hi> who for more than a year had left her in ſome ſort of quiet, to begin a perſecution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſh, which time ſeem'd to have miti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated, and now to recall into his me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory a man whom he had always en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to baniſh from it. An Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer of the Guards unriddl'd the myſtery to her, telling her that <hi>Zingis</hi> was very lately ſurpris'd at one of the Gates of the Palace, on the banks of the <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zangi,</hi> where <hi>Zamar</hi> had heard him ſpeak from a Terrace where ſhe was walking. That ſhe perceiving by his Diſcourſe, that he was returned to <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balu,</hi> for the ſake of the Princeſs, had
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:55009:5"/>order'd him to be aſſaulted, that his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour being over-power'd by number, they had overwhelm'd, tho' not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd, him, and that he was carried la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den with Irons to a great Tower, in which the vileſt Malefactors were uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſhut up.</p>
            <p>This Diſcourſe pierc'd the Soul of <hi>Taxila</hi> with a new Grief, ſhe bid the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar</hi> withdraw, and ſuffering her ſelf to fall into <hi>Axione</hi>'s arms, a Maid whom ſhe tenderly loved, becauſe ſhe was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together lovely: Ah! my dear <hi>Axione,</hi> ſaid ſhe unto her, the fatal accident which I ſo much fear'd, hath now befaln us, and the generous <hi>Zingis</hi> is in the chains of the implacable <hi>Zamar.</hi> Alas! I ſupported his abſence patiently, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it remov'd him out of the reach of that barbarous enemy; but he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipitateth himſelf into her hands, and it is the paſſion that he hath always had for me that driveth him back again.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:55009:6"/>I enjoy'd all kind of ſweetneſs in think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he lov'd me, and that I had no cauſe to be apprehenſive of any dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for him. I reckon'd up his Servi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, that I might recompenſe them with a moſt tender affection, and endured the importunities of <hi>Timur,</hi> hoping that Heaven would not abandon me to a Man ſo little worthy of me.</p>
            <p>The afflicted <hi>Taxila</hi> accompanied theſe words with a torrent of Tears, and the fair <hi>Axione,</hi> who, becauſe of the liberty which the Princeſs of <hi>Tartary</hi> gave her, and the noble Motions which animated her Soul, uſed all decent free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom with her, ſaid unto her all that ſhe judg'd proper to moderate her Grief. No, <hi>Axione,</hi> replied the fair Princeſs, we can no longer entertain any hope. My Father is faint-hearted, <hi>Zamar</hi> hath her Victim in her Power, <hi>Timur</hi> hath no Virtue, and the Heavens are reſolv'd to convince me to what heighth they
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:55009:6"/>are irritated againſt me. But, Madam, continued <hi>Axione,</hi> D'ye believe that the King will abjure Equity altogether, and that he will give ſo juſt a cauſe to ſo many Princes that have their Eyes upon him, during their abode at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balu,</hi> to deteſt his Cruelty. <hi>Axione,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Taxila,</hi> the Princes you ſpeak of are naturally baſe, and are moreover incens'd againſt the Valour of <hi>Zingis,</hi> who hath made them Slaves, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon them the Tributes that ſupport <hi>Zamar</hi>'s pride. Madam, anſwered <hi>Ax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ione,</hi> among the Kings whom we ſee here, there may perhaps be ſome that are brave and generous. 'Tis true, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied the Princeſs, that the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> hath a merit that diſtinguiſheth him from the reſt; together with that, added <hi>Axione,</hi> he hath Power, and I am perſuaded that he will attempt any thing for <hi>Zingis,</hi> for he is a lover of Virtue, and cannot endure Injuſtice.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:55009:7"/>
            <p>Whilſt theſe two amiable Perſons entertained one another in this manner, <hi>Zamar</hi> had the pleaſure to ſee her ſelf Miſtreſs of the Deſtiny of a Man who had ſo much curb'd her inſolency. <hi>Und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan</hi> had a great ſhare in her joy, and <hi>Timur</hi> triumphed unworthily over the misfortunes of a generous Rival, to whom he was obliged for his Life and Liberty.</p>
            <p>The day publiſhed the aſtoniſhing News among the <hi>Tartars.</hi> Thoſe who had ſeen <hi>Zingis,</hi> both in time of War and at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> prayed for his Ruin or Safety, according to their different in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations; but there were very few who would not have willingly reſcued him from the preſent Danger.</p>
            <p>Aſſoon as they could have acceſs to <hi>Undkan,</hi> the Kings of <hi>Tanguth, Cerguth, Ergimul,</hi> and <hi>Ung,</hi> waited upon him, and after them <hi>Philing</hi> King of <hi>Thibet.</hi> The firſt four expreſt a great deal of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:55009:7"/>joy for the captivity of his Enemy, and the laſt, who with an independent King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom much more conſiderable than the reſt, had alſo inclinations infinitely more noble and generous, ſpoke boldly in <hi>Zingis</hi>'s favour, and openly made it appear, that without knowing his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, he was full of Reſpect and Eſteem for his Virtue, and for that glorious Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putation, which had render'd his name ſo famous in <hi>Aſia. Undkan</hi> frown'd at <hi>Philing</hi>'s diſcourſe; and <hi>Zamar</hi> who heard it, from that time looked upon him as a ſuſpected Perſon. Never any could diſcover in him inclinations un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becoming a King. His Perſon was perfectly handſom, his Realms were of a vaſt extent, and owned no other Superiour. The neighbourhood of <hi>China,</hi> which bordered on his Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, was able to give him very great Advantages, in calling to his Aſſiſtance a People, who being often aſſaulted
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:55009:8"/>by the <hi>Tartars,</hi> had hitherto kept on the defenſive ſide, but long'd for a oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to humble them. All theſe rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons render'd the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtable to the <hi>Tartar,</hi> who anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him calmly, That <hi>Zingis</hi> was a Trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, and that the ſecurity of his Crown obliged him to keep him in Priſon. <hi>Philing</hi> did not think fit to importune further an incens'd King and Queen at preſent, in behalf of a Man whom he knew but imperfectly, and he went out looking diſdainfully on four Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, who diſhonoured their Character in baſely flattering <hi>Undkan</hi> and <hi>Zamar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Philing</hi> from thence went ſtrait to the Princeſs, whither his Heart often call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, but by reaſon of the Orders al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready given out, he could neither be permitted to ſee her, nor the amiable <hi>Axione.</hi> From thence he went to ſee <hi>Almundzar,</hi> an illuſtrious <hi>Tartar,</hi> in whom he had found a great deal of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:55009:8"/>Virtue, who governed <hi>Tartary</hi> by the profound Knowledge which he had of its moſt ſecret Affairs, and whom <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> upon that account did not love. He was a ſincere Friend of <hi>Zingis,</hi> and <hi>Philing</hi> found with him a faithful Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of that Prince, who having found means to get off in the obſcurity of the night, was come to ſollicit <hi>Almundzar</hi> to labour for his Maſter's Liberty. The generous <hi>Tartar</hi> had received him per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly well: but he feared with reaſon to be unable to do any thing for <hi>Zingis,</hi> againſt the fierce and ſubtle <hi>Zamar.</hi> They were upon this ſubject when the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> enter'd. Generous <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar,</hi> ſaid he at firſt to the Favourite of <hi>Undkan,</hi> What ſhall we do for the Illuſtrious <hi>Zingis,</hi> againſt ſo many im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable enemies? Hatred, Subtilty, and Treachery, are arm'd againſt him; and it's our Duty, whom Heaven hath favoured with more reaſonable inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:55009:9"/>to unite Virtue, Friendſhip, and Sincerity for his Aſſiſtance. The Squire of <hi>Zingis,</hi> who knew not <hi>Philing,</hi> and admir'd his good Mien, was raviſhed to hear him ſpeak in that manner. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar</hi> aſſur'd the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> that he was ready to hazard his Fortune and Life for the Service of <hi>Zingis;</hi> but withal that he knew nothing that could counterpoiſe the power of <hi>Zamar.</hi> I am ignorant of the particulars of <hi>Zingis</hi> his Life, ſaid <hi>Philing,</hi> and am only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupy'd with that ſhining Merit, of which Fame ſpeaketh ſo advantageouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: but, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> Cannot you inform me better? There is a Man, my Lord, replied <hi>Almundzar,</hi> pointing unto the faithful Squire of <hi>Zingis,</hi> who can bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than I give you that ſatisfaction. Yes, my Lord, added <hi>Zerbin,</hi> with a reſpectful bow, and I will do my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter a ſenſible pleaſure, to make him known to a Prince ſuch as you. <hi>Philing</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:55009:9"/>cauſed <hi>Zerbin</hi> to withdraw into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Chamber, to leave <hi>Almundzar</hi> in liberty to ſet about the Affairs with which he was uſually buſied, and having conveniently ſeated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Zerbin</hi> began his Diſcourſe in this manner.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>Zingis</hi> and the Princeſs <hi>Taxila.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YOU know, my Lord, that may Maſter is the Son of <hi>Sukuh,</hi> or <hi>Bahadur,</hi> ſirnam'd the <hi>Warriour,</hi> King of the <hi>Monguls;</hi> and you are not igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant that amongſt the reſt of the <hi>Aſiatick</hi> Nations, theſe have made themſelves be diſtinguiſhed by the undauntedneſs of their Courage, and the ſtrict Unity which they preſerve among themſelves. <hi>Bahadur</hi> is of the Linage of our moſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:55009:10"/>ancient Kings, the worthy Succeſſour of innumerable Heroes, the Terror of his Enemies, and Darling of his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. His Dominions are of a vaſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. The River <hi>Tartar</hi> and Lake of <hi>Coras</hi> render a great part of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try fertile, and that deſart Region which comprehendeth <hi>Bargu,</hi> and reacheth to the Sea of <hi>Tartary,</hi> is almoſt unknown to thoſe who border on <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Realms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bahadur</hi> had two Children of the Queen his Wife; the famous <hi>Zingis</hi> whom Fortune doth now expoſe in ſo cruel a manner, and the Princeſs <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie</hi> who was carried away by Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers at three years of age, in a Voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age which the Queen made to ſeek a place, the Air of which might be advantageous to their Health, which was in a languiſhing Condition. The loſs of the innocent <hi>Zenelie</hi> brought her with Sorrow to her Grave, leaving the young <hi>Zingis</hi> the only Conſolation of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:55009:10"/>her afflicted Husband. He was firſt called <hi>Temuzin;</hi> but there appeared in him even in his Infancy, ſo much Great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Soul and Courage, that the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple named hin <hi>Zingis,</hi> which is a Name given only to extraordinary Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bahadur</hi> enjoying a Son ſo worthy of his Affection, did not deſire a more numerous Poſterity, and made the Prince <hi>Zingis</hi> the Object of all his Cares, who in few years became perfectly well accompliſhed. The King with a great deal of Pleaſure ſaw his excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Qualities increaſe together. He knew by his firſt ſetting out, that he would not degenerate from ſo many Great Men, whoſe Blood ſtream'd in his Veins, ſeeing he aſpired unto true Glory, loved Virtue above all things, and bewraied only generous Inclinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. When he had attained the ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teenth year of his Age, he appeared of ſo graceful a Mien, that never any like
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:55009:11"/>him had hitherto been ſeen. <hi>Bahadur</hi> delighted in his preſence; but the young Prince who had thus far lived a peaceful Life, and whoſe Courage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired Buſineſs of greater Noiſe, began to think of leaving his Father for ſome time. My Lord, ſaid he, one day un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, Are you not ſenſible that I owe ſomething to the Honour which I have to be your Son? Hitherto I have been able only to teſtify my Reſpect unto you; but, my Lord, this is not ſufficient to ſatisfy the Blood that ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mateth us. The profound Peace which the <hi>Monguls</hi> enjoyed by your Valour, doth not permit me to live at <hi>Molg</hi> in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petual ſloth: we might one day bluſh, and even perhaps ſuffer for it. 'Tis time that I ſhould learn the only Occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pation that is worthy of a Prince. If there be no War in <hi>Aſia,</hi> I muſt ſeek it in <hi>Europe,</hi> and return to you with a Name leſs unknown to the reſt of the World.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:55009:11"/>
               <p>This Diſcourſe flatter'd the great Courage of <hi>Bahadur,</hi> but the ſame time it frightned the tenderneſs of his Love. <hi>Zingis,</hi> replied he to the young Prince, Neither your illuſtrious Anceſtors, nor the moſt envious Nations, have as yet any thing to reproach you with, and you have been employ'd in a diligent Preparation for a glorious riper Age. I love to ſee you, and I fear to loſe you: But, my Son, notwithſtanding this, do not think that I will always detain you in a Country, which in the Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of the greateſt part of Mankind is more proper for Wild Beaſts, than for Princes, whom Heaven hath created with ſome Merit: I do not oppoſe that noble Emulation which anima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth you; but, my dear <hi>Zingis,</hi> wait a little longer; you know that the King of the <hi>Tartars</hi> doth threaten us; he is perhaps ready to declare himſelf our Enemy. The Tributes which he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteth of ſeveral Kings will certainly
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:55009:12"/>come as far as us; and then we will not want War. Alas, my Lord, ſaid <hi>Zingis</hi> interrupting him, How hard is it for a Man of my Age and Humour to delay ſuch Projects? I don't know whether the King of the <hi>Tartars</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foundeth us with the other Princes whom he would render his Vaſſals; but by what you have done, I believe he will conſider more than once upon it before he attack you. In the end, my Lord, theſe are but uncertain Conje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, and if you will not permit me to paſs the Limits of <hi>Tartary,</hi> ſuffer me to run through all the extent thereof, that I may inſtruct my ſelf by ſight of many rare things, which I have only confuſedly heard of.</p>
               <p>The King of the <hi>Monguls</hi> found ſo much reaſon in the Prince's Deſign, that he conſented at laſt to his depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, tho' not without doing himſelf a great deal of Violence; but upon Condition, that he ſhould not paſs the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:55009:12"/>Bounds of <hi>Tartary.</hi> He permitted him to viſit <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Court, with whom he had not yet any broil; and <hi>Zingis</hi> ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with what he had obtained, thought on nothing elſe but to make ready his Equipage. He would not carry along with him a great Train of Servants, becauſe a profound Peace reigned o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver all the Countries through which he deſigned to paſs. Seeing I had been educated near his Perſon, and favoured with his Friendſhip, I accompanied him, and we parted from <hi>Molg,</hi> as if we had left a Priſon.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing we viſited was the Burying-place of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Princes. The Tombs are ſituated in Hills which do not hinder a Traveller to behold from afar an infinite number of mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent Pyramids which overlook the tops of the Mountains. From thence coaſting along by the Deſarts of <hi>Belgian,</hi> we ſaw the Kingdoms of <hi>Tanguth</hi> and <hi>Ergimul,</hi> without ſtopping in any place,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:55009:13"/>or making our ſelves known, and took the way to <hi>Cambalu,</hi> where we deſign'd to make a longer abode.</p>
               <p>As we drew near to that City, we were told that <hi>Undkan</hi> was gone with all his Court to paſs the faireſt Seaſon of the Year at <hi>Cingui,</hi> a pleaſant Town ſeated on the River <hi>Pazantu:</hi> Seeing it was only for the Court that my Maſter was going to <hi>Cambalu,</hi> upon this News he directed his Journey towards <hi>Cingui.</hi> The Palace-royal is without the Town, and one of the moſt magnificent in all <hi>Tartary:</hi> The Gardens are vaſt and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly cultivated; the Waters add un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them a thouſand Embelliſhments; the Trees form a charming obſcurity, which the Sun in many places can ſcarce penetrate, and there one may walk at all hours. We diſcovered the Royal Houſe from a good diſtance, and <hi>Zin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> fatigu'd with the heat, ſeeing one of the Gates of the Garden open, and kept by none, had a mind to enter into
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:55009:13"/>it and refreſh himſelf ſome moments, pointing with his hand to a place where he commanded us to wait for him. Although he had already made a great Journey, there was nothing neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected about him, and the magnificence of his Habit ſetting off the luſtre of his good Mien, one may ſay that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to be ſomething more than hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane.</p>
               <p>He admired the Beauty of theſe Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, which certainly is extraordinary, he walk'd in them with pleaſure, and thought of returning to us, when croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing an Alley, he ſaw at the end thereof ſeveral perſons together, and diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd amongſt the reſt ſome Women. As he is nothing leſs than fearful, he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vanc'd with a great deal of boldneſs, and as he drew nearer, he perceiv'd that theſe Women were of the higheſt Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, by the reſpect that was ſhew'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them: He was deſirous to know more of them, and therefore walked
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:55009:14"/>faſter; but a Man breaking off from the reſt came up to him, and looking upon him with a diſdainful air; Ho! Who art thou, ſaid he unto him haughtily, that violating the ſacred Laws of the place, comeſt inſolently to fail in the reſpect thou oweſt to the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty of the Princeſs of <hi>Tartary?</hi> Art thou ignorant that no Stranger dareth to appear before her, without being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduced according to the uſual Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoms? and is it to brave thoſe who follow her that thou comeſt thus to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe thy ſelf to our juſt Fury?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zingis</hi> was not accuſtom'd unto ſuch Diſcourſes, and this manner of accoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him ſurpriz'd him: His Action ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd unto him innocent, and the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars</hi> incivility incenſing him: I am a Man, reply'd he, who am not born to give an account of what I pretend to do: I would juſtifie my ſelf to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, but I do not know how to give that ſatisfaction to the Subjects of <hi>Undkan.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:55009:14"/>
               <p>He who heard <hi>Zingis,</hi> was too haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not to be incens'd with that Anſwer; 'twas <hi>Timur,</hi> whom the Titles of King of <hi>Tendur,</hi> and Son of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Queen, had ſwell'd with Pride even to Inſolency; and though that Character of Grandeur which appear'd over all the Perſon of the <hi>Mongul</hi> Prince, ought to have ſtay'd his hand, ſeeing himſelf back'd in his baſe Deſign, he drew his Sword, and lifted up his Arm to ſtrike <hi>Zingis;</hi> but how fatal had his Raſhneſs like to have prov'd unto him: The terrible <hi>Zingis</hi> prevented him by ſo heavy a blow on the Head that he laid him quite ſtun'd at his Feet, and had it not been for the thickneſs of his Head-Tire, he would never have afterwards diſturb'd the quiet of my Maſter.</p>
               <p>The Fall of <hi>Timur</hi> made a great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of the Guards run thither, who would have ſeiz'd upon <hi>Zingis:</hi> He defended himſelf valiantly, but never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs could not have preſerv'd himſelf
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:55009:15"/>from proving what Vertue hath cauſe to fear from perſons altogether void of it, if <hi>Undkan</hi> had not appear'd in the ſame Alley. At firſt he was inform'd of the cauſe of this Diſorder, and find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it ſo ſmall, he was ſorry for what had befaln <hi>Timur;</hi> and having but too good an opinion of him, who fear'd danger ſo little, he approach'd unto him with the Princeſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Undkan</hi> hath a goodly Preſence, able to inſpire even thoſe who do not know him, with reſpect; but it was the Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Taxila,</hi> and not the preſence of her Father, that made the <hi>Mongul</hi> Prince render his Arms. This charming ſight ſurpriz'd him in ſuch a manner, that he found himſelf unable to abſtain from gazing upon her, and from yielding up his young Heart to thoſe glorious Fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters which Fortune had prepar'd for him. <hi>Undkan</hi> who had not as yet bid adieu to Generoſity, look'd upon my Maſter with admiration, and <hi>Zingis</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:55009:15"/>accoſting him with a Grace that was natural to him; I perceive, my Lord, ſaid he, that you are the King of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and it is only to you that I am oblig'd to juſtifie my ſelf. I am <hi>Zingis</hi> Prince of the <hi>Monguls,</hi> and came into your Dominions with a purpoſe to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a while with you as a Friend and Allie. Paſſing by theſe Walls, by chance I obſerv'd an open Door, and not knowing the Cuſtoms of the place, I enter'd without deliberation into a place I judg'd free, and was affronted by a man, who is as ignorant of his du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to Strangers, as I am of the Cuſtoms of your Kingdoms.</p>
               <p>My Maſter's Diſcourſe ſurpriz'd <hi>Und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan:</hi> He had not a more conſiderable Allie than the King of the <hi>Monguls,</hi> and it was a great Honour to him to ſee that King's Son at his Court, being withal the handſomeſt and moſt love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Prince that his Eyes had ever yet beheld. I knew well that you were
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:55009:16"/>none of our <hi>Tartars,</hi> anſwer'd he, for none of them are ſo handſom as you. But, my Lord, that which according to our Laws would be a Crime in an ordinary Stranger, is none in the Prince of the <hi>Monguls,</hi> whom I will always behold with pleaſure at <hi>Cingui, Camba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lu,</hi> and through all the Extent of my Empire. Ac theſe words he embrac'd him, and preſenting him to the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs; <hi>Taxila,</hi> ſaid he unto her, Entreat the Prince <hi>Zingis</hi> to forget the bad Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception he met with upon your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. My Maſter, who found all his Wrath aſſwaged, and his natural fierce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs yielding to <hi>Taxila</hi>'s Charms, ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted her kneeling, and ask'd Pardon of her for the Errour his Ignorance had betray'd him into. The Princeſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd, That ſhe could add nothing to what her Father had ſaid; and my Maſter who could not withdraw his Eyes from ſo charming an Object, did already feel the powerful Impreſſions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:55009:16"/>which her extraordinary Beauty made upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Timur</hi> was come to himſelf again, and <hi>Zingis</hi> hearing that he was the Queen's Son, Accoſted him with an Air that had nothing of an Enemy in it: I am very ſorry, my Lord, ſaid he unto him, for having been engag'd in an Anger, which I entreat you would forget, and pleaſe to be reconcil'd to a Prince, who did not deſign in coming to <hi>Cingui,</hi> to create unto himſelf ſuch E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies as you are. At theſe words he offer'd to embrace him, and though <hi>Timur</hi> receiv'd him coldly, the Preſence of the King hinder'd him from reſiſting my Maſter's advance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zamar</hi> came afterwards, and was in a few words inform'd of the Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture that had happened. <hi>Undkan</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented <hi>Zingis</hi> unto her, and ſhe could not hinder her ſelf from entertaining a ſecret Reſentment of the Affront her Son had receiv'd. Nevertheleſs ſhe
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:55009:17"/>appear'd civil unto my Maſter, who not having his Eyes open but to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>template <hi>Taxila,</hi> had not leiſure to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the Queen of <hi>Tartary</hi>'s Actions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Undkan,</hi> who had ſecret Deſigns, would not ſuffer <hi>Zingis</hi> to go out of his Palace, and was not ſorry to have in his power ſo dear an Hoſtage of the King of the <hi>Monguls.</hi> We had Orders to wait upon our Prince, who was plac'd in one of the faireſt Apartments, and quickly judg'd that this Adventure would ere-long be the cauſe of many others.</p>
               <p>He was in a little time advanc'd by all the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the Princeſs had a judgment too juſt not to diſtinguiſh his Merit: They liv'd in greater Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity at <hi>Cingui</hi> than at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Court was not ſo numerous. <hi>Undkan,</hi> who was deſirous to gain the Affection of a conſiderable Prince, that he might obtain of him by Sweetneſs, what he pretended to impoſe upon
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:55009:17"/>others by force, neglected nothing that might pleaſe the young <hi>Zingis.</hi> He ſought all occaſions of entertaining him with Pleaſures agreeable to his Inclina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and ſeeing that <hi>Timur</hi> ſtill kept up his coldneſs, he entreated him to conſtrain himſelf: And he, though not without Repugnance, by the Advice of a politick Mother, who hop'd to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain for this Son one of the greateſt Crowns in <hi>Aſia</hi> from <hi>Undkan,</hi> did what the King deſir'd him.</p>
               <p>As for my Maſter, he wholly gave himſelf up unto Love. The more he ſaw <hi>Taxila,</hi> the greater Empire ſhe gain'd over him: His Heart full of an ardent Paſſion, began to feel Pains be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unknown to him, and fearing as yet more cruel Vexations, he became reſtleſs as ſoon as he began to love. He was the Son of a Prince that could de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny him nothing, but <hi>Taxila</hi> was the Daughter of a Man, that deſtin'd her for <hi>Timur;</hi> and the Dominions of this
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:55009:18"/>Rival were much inferiour to the Kingdom of the <hi>Monguls,</hi> he was a King and the Son of <hi>Zamar</hi> who had all power over <hi>Undkan.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In the end they left <hi>Cingui</hi> to return to <hi>Cambalu:</hi> There the Divertiſements chang'd Face; inſtead of Walks, they were taken up with Plays and publick Spectacles. <hi>Taxila</hi> had ſeveral Maids of Quality about her: But a few days before our Arrival at <hi>Cingui,</hi> ſhe had been preſented with an unknown Girl admirably Fair, and perfectly Lovely, whom the Princeſs ſoon diſtinguiſh'd from all the reſt, by a Friendſhip full of Eſteem and Confidence. The Men who made the greateſt Figure at Court, were <hi>Timur, Almundzar,</hi> and <hi>Omir</hi> Prince of <hi>Brema,</hi> who had been brought young to <hi>Cambalu,</hi> the King of <hi>Tartary</hi> having poſſeſs'd himſelf of his Father's Dominions, who had loſt his life in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending them. There were alſo <hi>Bazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an, Mirantes, Ozran, Ziphanes,</hi> and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:55009:18"/>others. My Maſter perceiv'd at firſt the great Merit of <hi>Almundzar,</hi> and united himſelf in a ſtrict Friendſhip with the Prince of <hi>Brema.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Whilſt ſome Months paſt over in this manner, thoſe among the <hi>Tartars</hi> whom my Maſter frequented were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly ſenſible of his Worth, and eſteem'd him perfectly well. For him, his only Care was to pleaſe <hi>Taxila,</hi> who remark'd his Earneſtneſs in ſerving her, though ſhe was diligently obſerv'd by <hi>Timur,</hi> who enjoy'd the Priviledges which his Mother's Credit gave him, and often put the Patience of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Tartary</hi> to a cruel Teſt. For thinking himſelf ſecure of a Happineſs he did not merit, he ſpoke before her with an inſupportable Boldneſs, and <hi>Taxila</hi> comparing the ſubmiſſive Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedure of the Prince of the <hi>Monguls,</hi> with the arrogant Behaviour of the Son of <hi>Zamar,</hi> ſhe obſerv'd the ſame differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence between them, that Nature had
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:55009:19"/>put between their Perſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zingis</hi> had too much Reſpect, not to impoſe upon himſelf an exact Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion: Although he was a Prince, and in a Condition to pretend unto all Things, yet he would not precipitate a Declaration of his Love, leſt it ſhould irritate the Princeſs, and waited till he had by his Services prepar'd her to give him a favourable Audience. The Heart of the Princeſs found it ſelf on <hi>Zingis</hi> ſide, and her Averſion for <hi>Timur</hi> receiv'd a great Augmentation ſince my Maſter's Arrival.</p>
               <p>On a Day which <hi>Timur</hi> look'd upon as his own, becauſe it was <hi>Taxila</hi>'s Birth-day, he prepared Divertiſements for all the Court, and among the reſt extraordinary Shews upon the <hi>Poliſangi.</hi> A thouſand gilded Barks covered the River: Every one wore what Colours he pleas'd, and nothing was to be ſeen but Cyphers and Devices on the Strea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers; the Cordage was of Gold and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:55009:19"/>Silk, the Oars cover'd over with ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning Pictures; and theſe little Barks full of Magnificent Court, form'd the moſt pleaſant Shew in the World.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs would have willingly diſpens'd with all this Gallantry of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur,</hi> but the fear of incenſing oblig'd her to accept of it, and ſhe was even forc'd to appear on this Feſtival with all the moſt far-ferch'd helps of Art. <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur</hi> in all his Equipage obſerv'd a Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence that tended to Prodigality, and my Maſter with leſs Affectation had greater Advantages. <hi>Zamar</hi> did not ſlight theſe Shews as ſhe had done many others, and <hi>Undkan</hi> to do his Wife a Pleaſure, honour'd them with his Preſence. The Amorous <hi>Zingis</hi> had the Vexation to ſee the Name of his Rival every where intermixt with that of <hi>Taxila,</hi> and to think that ſo much Beauty and Vertue was deſtin'd for a Man, in whom he ſaw nothing that could render him worthy of them,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:55009:20"/>and theſe Conſiderations did coſt him many a heavy Groan, which the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs ſometimes over-heard.</p>
               <p>In the end, my Lord, that Day which <hi>Timur</hi> was deſirous to Solemnize in an extraordinary manner was Remarkable for a memorable Adventure, which had like to have prov'd Fatal. All were taken up with the Pleaſures prepar'd for them on the River; a harmonious Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody fill'd the Air, when by an unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected Misfortune, the Boat in which the Princeſs was alone with <hi>Axione</hi> the unknown Maid that was become ſo dear unto her, becauſe theſe little Barks were able to bear but four perſons at moſt with the Rowers, was o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verturn'd, being daſh'd againſt ſome of the reſt, and <hi>Taxila</hi> and <hi>Axione</hi> were expos'd to ſo great a Danger, that all there preſent believ'd there was no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medy. Cries of Grief ſucceeded the Harmony of the Inſtruments. <hi>Timur,</hi> the cowardly <hi>Timur</hi> did nothing but
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:55009:20"/>excite ſome of his Train to dive for <hi>Taxila</hi> amongſt the Waves; but the courageous <hi>Zingis</hi> animated with other Sentiments, threw himſelf into the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and nimbly cutting the Water, received the Princeſs in his Arms, juſt in the nick that ſhe appear'd again, and when perhaps ſhe was going to ſink for ever into the bottom of the River: His Action was ſo quick, that none of the reſt were able to prevent him. The Prince of <hi>Brema</hi> who was with him render'd the ſame Service to <hi>Axione,</hi> and being equally happy on this Occaſion, they were full of joy to have reſcu'd from Death the two moſt Amiable Perſons in the World. The Danger was great, for the Men who fell into the Water with <hi>Taxila</hi> periſh'd, becauſe of the little Care that was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to help them, their Negligence in ſome meaſure meriting their unhappy Fortune.</p>
               <p>This Accident diſturb'd all the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnity:
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:55009:21"/>
                  <hi>Undkan</hi> being Alarm'd, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to regain the Shore; the Princeſs and <hi>Axione</hi> were carried thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther almoſt without ſenſe, and <hi>Timur</hi> incapable of, Shame, had the Boldneſs to approach unto them. <hi>Zamar</hi> who had beheld with Envy my Maſter's A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, and who began to penetrate into the ſecret intereſt of his Heart, appear'd confus'd for her Son, and could not forbear murmuring at his Cowardli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs opened her Eyes and came, to her ſelf again; when they had laid her in a Bed, ſhe ask'd News of <hi>Axione,</hi> whom they had tended with the ſame Care, and then betook her ſelf to the Reſt that was neceſſary for her: She paſt the Night ſweetly, and finding her ſelf perfectly recover'd in the Morning, ſhe ask'd her Maids, To whom among the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſhe ow'd her Life. Although ſhe had no good Opinion of <hi>Timur,</hi> ſhe fear'd ſhe had
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:55009:21"/>receiv'd ſo conſiderable a Service from him, and being inform'd that it was <hi>Zingis</hi> that had ſav'd her, having pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented all others with a Precipitation full of Zeal, ſhe felt a ſecret Joy, and thank'd Heaven for it. They did not fail to tell her that the King of <hi>Tendur</hi> did not ſo much as hazard himſelf for her, and ſhe was much joy'd to think that ſhe had no Obligation to him.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as Day appear'd, <hi>Axione</hi> wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon the Princeſs, who embrac'd her tenderly: <hi>Undkan</hi> had declar'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to my Maſter, how much he was ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible of what he had done for <hi>Taxila. Zamar</hi> who was excellently skill'd in the Art of Conſtraining her ſelf, thank'd him alſo, and <hi>Timur</hi> ſaid ſomething of that nature to him, notwithſtanding his Confuſion, but it was not they who he wiſh'd might be ſenſible of it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taxila</hi> aroſe, and willing to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Timur</hi>'s private Importunities, ſhe went out of her Apartment, juſt as the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:55009:22"/>Queen was coming to ſee her; and meeting her in a common Gallery, Madam, ſaid <hi>Zamar</hi> to the Princeſs, I praiſe Heaven for the great Care it hath had of your Life, and I aſſure you, that at that moment when I ſaw it in danger, I would have heartily hazar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded mine own to preſerve it. You would have done much more, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, replyed <hi>Taxila</hi> with a modeſt Smile, than many Men were able to do, and you ſee that in the middle of my Fathers Dominions, there were only found two ſtranger Princes gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous enough to deſpiſe the Danger. But, Madam, added ſhe, with a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found Reverence full of Grace and Majeſty, your Days are more precious than mine, and too many Illuſtrious Perſons have an intereſt in them, to let them be expos'd to the leaſt Danger, and I am as much oblig'd to your good Intentions, as if they had produced other Effects.</p>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:55009:22"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zamar</hi> perceiv'd by this Diſcourſe that <hi>Taxila</hi> had much Gratitude for <hi>Zingis,</hi> and Scorn for <hi>Timur;</hi> but not being reſolv'd to inſiſt longer on this Subject, ſhe was entreating the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs to return unto her Apartment, when the King paſt by, followed by <hi>Timur, Omir,</hi> my Maſter, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> and ſeveral others.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taxila</hi> bluſh'd extreamly; her fair Eyes which as yet look'd languiſhing, told <hi>Zingis</hi> in an obliging manner, that ſhe knew what he had done for her: and <hi>Timur</hi> had the mortification to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark that ſhe did not ſo much as turn them towards him. My Daughter, ſaid <hi>Undkan</hi> to her, you have made me paſs the Night with a great deal of anxiety, which the good Condition in which I now ſee you, doth agreeably diſſipate. Mean-time, methinks you ſhould not have left your Apartment ſo ſoon. My Lord, anſwer'd the Princeſs, a little Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe cannot hurt me, and I feel no
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:55009:23"/>more any remainder of my Illneſs. The King made an obliging Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to the lovely <hi>Axione,</hi> which ſhe receiv'd with much Reſpect, and all this goodly Company went with <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> becauſe the Hour of Dinner ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd.</p>
               <p>My Maſter, who ſaw that the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs being watch'd by <hi>Timur,</hi> could not be entertain'd by another, retired, and after Dinner the King of <hi>Tendur</hi> Accoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her without any Obſtacle, had the liberty to ſay what he pleas'd: He look'd a great while upon the Princeſs with a premeditated Air, and then looking downwards; The ſame Day on which Heaven gave you to the World, as the richeſt Preſent it could beſtow, had like to have been the laſt of your Life: Madam, ſaid he, and I tremble to think of the Danger which threatned you. All the World did not believe it ſo great as you did, my Lord, reply'd <hi>Taxila</hi> diſdainfully, and the
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:55009:23"/>Princes of the <hi>Monguls</hi> and <hi>Brema</hi> ſhew'd that they deſpis'd it, in expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing themſelves thereto. It's true, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, anſwered <hi>Timur,</hi> Red with Anger and Shame, that they ſhew'd ſome fearleſneſs; but they at that time had all their Reaſon about them, whereas mine was diſturb'd by the moſt fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful of all Ideas: And all this Diſtur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bance and Trouble, my Lord, reply'd the Princeſs, with a malicious Smile, would have even let me periſh, had there not been found more unconcern'd perſons, and leſs intereſted for my Life. I ſee well, anſwer'd <hi>Timur,</hi> that you would enhanſe the price of a Service great indeed, but which a thouſand o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers would have render'd unto you. All the World would have done it, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the King of <hi>Tendur,</hi> ſaid <hi>Taxila,</hi> interrupting him; but, my Lord, be not incens'd if I have ſome acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for this Service, which well deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth it; ſeeing I promiſe that I will
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:55009:24"/>make reckoning of your trouble of Mind, and even of the fear it cauſed in you. <hi>Timur</hi> would have anſwer'd, and perhaps would have done it without reſpect; but a multitude of people that came to ſee the Princeſs hinder'd him, and he went out full of Confuſion. <hi>Taxila</hi> who ſaw the Day was very fair, went down to the Palace-Gardens, and walk'd there for ſome time: Thoſe that follow'd her, remarking that ſhe was deſirous to be alone, retir'd a good diſtance from her; She ſat down at the end of a Terrace that faceth the <hi>Poliſangi,</hi> and obſerving the place where ſhe had almoſt been drown'd; <hi>Axione,</hi> ſaid ſhe to that fair Maid, as we after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards came to know, as couragious as you are, do you not quake, when you look upon that River? My Princeſs, anſwer'd <hi>Axione,</hi> I proteſt unto you that I was troubled only for you, and that with the knowledge that remain'd with me, though I believ'd my own Death
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:55009:24"/>certain, yet the Thought of yours was that which moſt tormented me. You are too good a Friend, my dear <hi>Axione,</hi> reply'd <hi>Taxila,</hi> preſſing her hand, and I cannot enough requite that tender and generous Motion of forgetting your ſelf for me. I may truly ſay, anſwered <hi>Axione,</hi> ſighing, that you are one of the moſt powerful Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that make me deſire Life, and one, added ſhe with watry Eyes, which at preſent ought to carry it over all the reſt. You render mine dear unto me, reply'd the Princeſs; but, <hi>Axione,</hi> I don't know whether I ought to rejoyce that it is lengthen'd. Ah, Madam! cry'd out <hi>Axione,</hi> why ſhould not you be ſatisfied with a Happineſs that is precious to all reaſonable perſons? A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las! anſwered <hi>Taxila,</hi> a Happineſs that muſt be Sacrific'd to <hi>Timur,</hi> can pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe me no Satisfaction. What Man, among all the Men of the World, doth the King my Father chooſe? Shall I
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:55009:25"/>be the Victim of that Power which his Weakneſs gives unto <hi>Zamar?</hi> Beſides the little Inclination that naturally I have for <hi>Timur;</hi> he doth nothing that he ought to do to win me; he thinks I am his by duty, and you ſee how he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hav'd himſelf in our late Adventure; more in love with his Life than with the unhappy <hi>Taxila,</hi> he abandoneth her to an evident Danger, and leaveth to the Generoſity of others to Reſcue her. Ah! what can he ever expect from that Princeſs whoſe Preſervation he ſo faint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly neglected? O Heaven! O juſt Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, continued ſhe in a ſadder Tone! I who ſo much abhor Baſeneſs, will you permit me to fall into the power of the baſeſt of all Men? As the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs expreſſed her ſelf after this manner, my Maſter, who had heard that ſhe was in the Garden, appear'd with the Prince of <hi>Brema; Taxila</hi> perceiving, roſe up to meet them: <hi>Zingis</hi> preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Hand to her, after he had Saluted
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:55009:25"/>her. <hi>Omir</hi> render'd the ſame Office to <hi>Axione,</hi> and they continued their Walk. Well, Madam, ſaid my Maſter to the Princeſs, How do you find your ſelf after that cruel Accident? And you, my Lord, reply'd ſhe with a charming Sweetneſs, You who took ſo generous a part, and ſo advantage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous for me, in what condition is your Health? Though it had been attack'd by a Malady, anſwered <hi>Zingis,</hi> My joy that I had ſucceſsfully ſerv'd a great Princeſs, in whoſe Safety all the World ought to intereſt themſelves, would have entirely diſſipated it: Our Bodies are fitted for greater Fatigues; you ſuffered much, and I have reaſon to be troubled at it. I aſſure you, my Lord, reply'd <hi>Taxila,</hi> that there remaineth nothing of that Adventure with me, but the remembrance of the ſenſible Obligation that I have unto you. O, my Lord, added ſhe! with an Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that witneſs'd her Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:55009:26"/>what can I do to acquit my ſelf of it. It is too much that you remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber it, anſwer'd the Prince of the <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guls,</hi> and that Price is great enough to recompence more important Service. I do not know any that can be more worthy of my Remembrance, reply'd <hi>Taxila.</hi> —Madam, ſaid my Maſter, ſighing, and interrupting her, Although according to all Appearances, I have only labour'd for <hi>Timur,</hi> yet I cannot but look on Yeſterday as the happieſt Day of my Life. The Princeſs look'd downwards to hide ſome Tears which theſe Words forc'd from her, and which, nevertheleſs, <hi>Zingis</hi> perceived: He was grieved that he had touch'd her in ſo ſenſible a part, and continued thus; Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me, Madam, if I have nam'd the King of <hi>Tendur:</hi> I fear I have fail'd in the Reſpect I owe you. No, ſaid <hi>Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ila,</hi> interrupting him, But you have ſet before my Eyes an afflicting Idea, which I often endeavour to put out of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:55009:26"/>my Mind. You know the King my Father's Intentions concerning <hi>Timur:</hi> but, my Lord, you do not know mine, and you are doubtleſs ignorant, that I can't think of ſeeing my ſelf ſubjected to the Son of <hi>Zamar,</hi> without a mortal Grief. I am not reſolute enough to diſobey <hi>Undkan,</hi> and whatſoever it coſts me, I muſt, if he command me, ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice my ſelf. Judge, my Lord, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a natural Averſion, or rather in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincible Hatred for <hi>Timur,</hi> in what Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition I muſt needs be, when I think on my Father's Deſigns, and the Queen's Authority. This Freedom of the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs Charm'd my Maſter, and render'd him bolder. I confeſs, continued he, That there is nothing in <hi>Timur</hi> that is worthy of you, nor even in perſons much more accompliſh'd. O! What Man, Madam, amongſt all thoſe whom Nature and Fortune have moſt diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh'd by their Favours, could with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Crime aſpire unto the precious
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:55009:27"/>Advantage of not diſpleaſing you, or the Glory of poſſeſſing you one Day? My Lord, reply'd <hi>Taxila,</hi> I can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Merit where it is, and not draw a blame-worthy Pride from that which I have not: There are Men enough in the World who might juſtly pretend to the Alliance of the King of <hi>Tartary,</hi> and <hi>Timur</hi> himſelf would not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy of it for his Quality, if his evil Inclinations were not abſolutely in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compatible with mine. Though For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune ſhould authorize ſome Prince to offer unto you all that he poſſeſt, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded my Maſter, if his perſon had not wherewithal to touch your Heart, his other Advantages would be to no pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe; and there are Princes puiſſant enough who would ſigh before your Eyes, without daring to tell you that they Adore you. I would certainly be very Savage, reply'd the Princeſs of <hi>Tartary,</hi> to arm my ſelf with an unjuſt Fury againſt thoſe who had ſome Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:55009:27"/>for me, and I would need be free of all Paſſions, if I dared to boaſt of remaining always inſenſible. But, my Lord, continued ſhe, with a freer Air; this Subject would carry us too far, and I had rather ſpeak of the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation that I have unto you: If it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpire you with any Goodneſs for me, anſwered my Maſter, it will be very advantageous for me in the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces I am in, ſeeing that loving you with an ardent Paſſion, the beginnings of which I have carefully hid, I cannot hinder the Declaration of this Myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry from eſcaping in ſpight of all my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. My Lord, reply'd <hi>Taxila</hi> with a trouble, which gave no ſad Preſage unto my Maſter, I ſee the King, and that is all I ought to ſay unto you. And indeed <hi>Undkan</hi> appear'd, and <hi>Zingis</hi> could not continue: He knew well by the Air of the Princeſs, that ſhe had Confuſion without Anger, and for ſome Days afterwards, if he remark'd any
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:55009:28"/>Commotion in her Eyes, yet Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion had no part in it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Taxila</hi> was belov'd of all the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and the important Service that my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter had render'd unto her, made a great Impreſſion on all grateful Minds. That Nation look'd upon <hi>Timur</hi> with Scorn after his late baſe and cowardly Action. <hi>Undkan</hi> was even vexed to ſee that he render'd himſelf ſo little worthy of all the Advantages he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin'd for him; and could not forbear, as we knew by <hi>Almundzar,</hi> to ſpeak of it unto the Queen: but ſhe had ſo much power over him, that he paſt over the cowardlineſs of the King of <hi>Tendur,</hi> and reſolv'd to be a no leſs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Obſerver of his Promiſe.</p>
               <p>About that time <hi>Zamar,</hi> who was deſirous to extend the Limits of <hi>Tarta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> in hope to ſee her Son Maſter of it; inſinuated into <hi>Undkan,</hi> that it was a Shame to him, who was Lord of ſo much Power, not to exact of his Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:55009:28"/>the Tributes which he might eaſily impoſe upon them. The moſt part of theſe Kings have preſerv'd ſomewhat of the Fierceneſs of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Scythians,</hi> but have loſt all their Valour, of which you may in this Court ſee Examples in thoſe of <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guth, Tanguth, Ergimul,</hi> and <hi>Ung. Und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan</hi> gave their Miniſters to underſtand, that they ow'd ſomething more than a ſimple Embaſſie to his Grandeur, and that together with Homage, they muſt pay him an Annual Tribute. Theſe Strangers ask'd time to communicate this Affair to their Maſters; &amp; having in the end anſwer'd, That their Deſign was not to humble themſelves ſo low, they Retir'd into the Dominions of their Princes, and every-where were made great Preparations for War.</p>
               <p>The Kings of <hi>Tanguth, Cerguth,</hi> and <hi>Ergimul,</hi> could eaſily joyn their Forces, becauſe of the Neigbourhood of their Provinces, but he of <hi>Ung</hi> being more
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:55009:29"/>remote, and lying on the oppoſite ſide, was to make a Diverſion. Tho' <hi>Zingis</hi> had reaſon to believe, That the <hi>Monguls</hi> would have their turn next; yet lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving <hi>Taxila</hi> as he did, he would not remain idle in her Father's Court, and tho' he found injuſtice in <hi>Undkan</hi>'s At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt, yet Love hinder'd him from examining his Procedures rigorouſly. He ſoon determin'd to offer his Arm to the King of <hi>Tartary;</hi> and however afflicting his abſence from <hi>Taxila,</hi> might prove to his Heart, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to remove, that he might be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come more worthy of her.</p>
               <p>The Kings of <hi>Tanguth</hi> and <hi>Cerguth</hi> advanc'd to the Dominions of the King of <hi>Ergimul,</hi> who was firſt to be attack'd, being <hi>Undkan</hi>'s next Neighbour. There was need of two Armies, becauſe the King of <hi>Ung</hi> was alone, and <hi>Timur</hi>'s Kingdom being adjacent to that, it was to him that <hi>Undkan</hi> entruſted a part of his Forces to make that Conqueſt:
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:55009:29"/>But Experience taught him that he had put them in very ill Hands. The King of <hi>Tendur</hi> would have willingly ſtay'd at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> if his Mother more Coura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geous than he, had not excited him to his Duty: So with good Lieutenants and Warlike Troops he march'd to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Enemy whom he had to Vanquiſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zingis</hi> had the Command of no Army given him, as had <hi>Timur,</hi> though he was much more capable of it: <hi>Und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan</hi> march'd in perſon, and my Maſter would take no Charge upon him, that he might fight near his Perſon.</p>
               <p>The Princeſſes beheld theſe Warlike Preparations with very different Agi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of Spirit. <hi>Zamar</hi> who knew that her Husband and Son were not of an humor to hazard themſelves, thought on their Departure without Alarms; but <hi>Taxila</hi> who already knew perfectly the Love and Courage of my Maſter, had not the ſame Tranquillity.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:55009:30"/>
               <p>Affairs being in this condition, <hi>Zin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> went to take his leave of her, and <hi>Timur</hi>'s preſent Occupations, freeing her for ſome time from his Importuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; He found none but <hi>Axione</hi> with her: Seeing they did not ſuſpect her, the Prince did not conſtrain his Love, and the Princeſs ſuffer'd her Sadneſs to appear. You are going to depart from us, my Lord, to purſue Victories which we may well be without. Ah! how covetous is the Ambition of <hi>Zamar,</hi> and how skilful is ſhe in finding out means to ſhed Blood? Seeing the Glory of the King your Father is concern'd, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, anſwer'd <hi>Zingis,</hi> thoſe who may loſe their Blood on this Occaſion, have no reaſon to repent it. Whatſoever be the Motives of a War, reply'd <hi>Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ila,</hi> it is ſtill grievous unto me: But, my Lord, the War which you now undertake, appeareth unto me ſo much the more cruel, that <hi>Timur</hi> will be deck'd with the Spoils thereof, which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:55009:30"/>will raiſe his Vanity to an extream In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolence. So long as the King liveth, continued my Maſter, he will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the Fruits thereof; and if Fortune put an end to his Life, I ſee few <hi>Tartars</hi> inclin'd to ſubmit themſelves to the Laws of <hi>Timur.</hi> I cannot flatter my ſelf, my Lord, anſwer'd <hi>Taxila,</hi> with a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter agitation of Mind than before, he wil Reign, the unhappy Aſcendant which over-ruleth my Deſtiny hath ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain'd, and would to the Heavens that my Death may prevent his Fortune. Ah! Madam, ſaid my Maſter, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupting her in a paſſionate manner, is it thus that you comfort a miſerable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, whoſe duty conſtraineth him to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low <hi>Undkan,</hi> &amp; who cannot depart from you but with intolerable Grief? What ſhall I do in the Extremity to which I now ſee my ſelf reduc'd? Shall I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main a cowardly and uſeleſs Spectator of a War which may expoſe <hi>Tartary</hi> unto ſome Diſorder, becauſe the proud
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:55009:31"/>
                  <hi>Timur</hi> layeth claim to it? and ſhall I behold the Father of <hi>Taxila,</hi> a Princeſs whom I adore, and for whom I would hazard a thouſand Lives, if they were in my power, ſhall I ſee him, I ſay, march to the War, without making a Rampart of my Body and Arms to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend him, becauſe he favoureth my Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val? In end, Madam, ſhall I ſtay at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> or ſhall I retire to the <hi>Monguls,</hi> to evite uncertain Evils, and merit that my Name be buried in oblivion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Men? Ah, my Princeſs! How unworthy ſhould I be to Sigh for you, and to bear theſe glorious Chains which I have receiv'd with ſo much pleaſure! Whatſoever the time to come may pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce, the preſent ordaineth me to ſerve the King of <hi>Tartary:</hi> My Fidelity and Zeal will perhaps make ſome impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion on his Soul: But, Madam, you are ſilent, and I ſee nothing in your Eyes but a Trouble that alarms me. What Misfortune can it preſage unto us? My
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:55009:31"/>Lord, anſwered <hi>Taxila,</hi> You ſee that it is an effect of my Weakneſs, your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons have overcome me, but they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſettle my Heart. Alas, <hi>Zingis!</hi> Was not I miſerable enough to hate <hi>Timur,</hi> if it be the will of Fate that I muſt be his, without loving.—<hi>Taxila</hi> bluſh'd, and could not go on, but her Eyes were the Interpreters of her Heart, and thoſe of the amorous <hi>Zingis</hi> read in them the happineſs for which he ſigh'd.</p>
               <p>Never was there Separation more tender on <hi>Zingis</hi>'s ſide, and more obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging on <hi>Taxila</hi>'s, than was that of theſe two illuſtrious Perſons: <hi>Timur</hi> did not give himſelf the trouble of ſo much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect and Niceneſs, he only in an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſant manner repeated what he had ſaid ſo often, and appear'd as inſolent, as if he had been aſſur'd of the Conqueſt of all the World.</p>
               <p>We found the three Kings joyn'd, and ready to give us Battel: Their Troops were refreſh'd with a long Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:55009:32"/>whereas <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Men were Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigu'd with climbing over the Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains and Woods. The Enemies were poſſeſt of advantageous Poſts, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd to be reſolute: Nevertheleſs fight we muſt. All that is related of the fabulous Heroes doth not ſurpaſs that which <hi>Zingis</hi> then did: <hi>Undkan</hi> look'd upon him as a Prodigy; 'twas his Valour alone which made Victory ſtill declare it ſelf in our Favour: He ſav'd <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Life, who againſt his will was engag'd among the Enemies, and after many Battels, he took the three Kings Priſoners on different Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, which put an end to the War on that ſide.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Undkan</hi> left the Prince Maſter of the Deſtiny of the Captives: He gave them not only their Lives, but alſo their Liberty; and contented himſelf to engage them to pay the Homage and Tribute which the King of <hi>Tartary</hi> had demanded of them: The Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:55009:32"/>of ſuch a Conquerour ſerv'd on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to animate them with a ſecret Rage againſt him: but <hi>Undkan</hi> after having publickly own'd, that it was to him alone that he ow'd the Glory of this Expedition, ſeeing his Enemies ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>du'd, disbanded his Troops, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn'd to <hi>Cambalu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fortune had not been ſo favourable to <hi>Timur,</hi> and the King of <hi>Ung</hi> with Forces inferiour to his, chas'd him out of his Provinces, and prepar'd to march towards thoſe which compoſe the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of <hi>Tendur.</hi> Theſe News afflicted <hi>Undkan,</hi> and my Maſter deſirous to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh as he had begun, paſt without ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping to the place where <hi>Timur</hi> was, brought him back to the Battel, and return'd to <hi>Cambalu</hi> after he had tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph'd over the King of <hi>Ung,</hi> as he had done over the reſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Undkan</hi> receiv'd him with great Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of Joy, and <hi>Zamar,</hi> although envious of his Glory, was oblig'd to
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:55009:33"/>teſtifie her Acknowlegment to him: but it was not their Applauſe that touch'd him, and <hi>Taxila</hi>'s Praiſes were of much higher Value in his Heart: A Year of abſence had as yet augmented her Beauty, and my Maſter at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn found her ſuch as his Ardour could have wiſh'd. I do not know if my Vows have had any part in your Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories, my Lord, ſaid ſhe unto him, when he went to ſalute her: But ſure I am, I have made very ardent and ſincere ones for you. I do not at all queſtion the Obligations which I have to your Goodneſs, Madam, anſwered <hi>Zingis,</hi> and certainly the Hope I had that I did not diſpleaſe you, hath ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd me more bold and brave than the Hope of poſſeſſing the <hi>Unners</hi> would have done. But, Madam, what will become of ſo much Love which your charming Beauties have inſpir'd me with, if <hi>Undkan</hi> be only favourable to the Son of <hi>Zamar?</hi> O, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:55009:33"/>of my Tenderneſs and Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment for you, interrupted <hi>Taxila,</hi> if in ſpight of me they give me to him whom I abhor? He is not ſenſible of his own Shame, and pretendeth to co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver himſelf with your Glory; and even my Father, notwithſtanding all that you have done for him, is capable to requite all with Ingratitude. 'Tis the knowledge that I have of his Injuſtice that afflicteth me; bemoan with me, my Lord, bemoan with me, and whatſoever come to paſs, believe me, I will be ever more miſerable than you. <hi>Timur</hi> then enter'd; he had not ſeen the Princeſs but with his Mother; his Gate was full of Haughtineſs, and he had receiv'd for a Reward of his Baſeneſs, new aſſuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of Happineſs; or rather <hi>Zamar,</hi> who deſirous to comfort him in his bad Fortune in War, and to diſſipate a gloomy Penſiveneſs which diſquieted him, had drawn from <hi>Undkan</hi> ſtronger Promiſes, That he would give <hi>Taxila</hi>
                  <pb n="62" facs="tcp:55009:34"/>unto her Son, than ever he had made unto her before. He was vex'd to ſee <hi>Zingis</hi> in a place, where from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth he was reſolv'd to Reign alone; and if he durſt have follow'd the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of his Soul, he would have at that inſtant told him his Mind, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of what paſt in the War retain'd him, and contenting himſelf with ſhewing him no Civility. We come from enriching the Crown of <hi>Tartary,</hi> Madam, ſaid he unto her, with ſeveral Tributes of Importance, and it is at preſent the only Crown in <hi>Aſia</hi> that can reckon great Kings amongſt its Subjects. You might ſpeak leſs generally, <hi>Timur,</hi> anſwer'd the Princeſs, with a diſdainful Coldneſs, worthy of the King of <hi>Tendur</hi>'s Arrogancy; and if Fame hath done you Juſtice, the King of <hi>Ung</hi> ought to have carried the ſame Advantages over you, which the Prince of the <hi>Monguls</hi> hath carry'd over him and the reſt.</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:55009:34"/>
               <p>Theſe Words did pierce the proud Son of <hi>Zamar</hi> to the quick, inſomuch that his Fury for a long time ſhut up his Mouth: But coming to himſelf a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, if you were more juſt and leſs pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judic'd, continu'd he, you would not take from the Arms of the King your Father, the Glory which is due unto them, to give it unto others; and I was not in ſo deſperate a Condition, when they came unto the Provinces of <hi>Ung,</hi> but I could have quickly ſubdued them. If they had followed my Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, reply'd the fair Princeſs with the ſame Coldneſs, they ſhould have given you all the time you had need of; and truly, my Lord, you ought to have taken it your ſelf. I don't know, ſaid my Maſter, whether I have any part in the obliging Words of the Princeſs, or in <hi>Timur</hi>'s Scorn; but this I know, that I would eſteem my ſelf much more Glorious in the one than Diſhonour'd by the other. My Lord,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:55009:35"/>added <hi>Taxila,</hi> I would certainly be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry unreaſonable, if I was the only per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in <hi>Tartary,</hi> that render'd not Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice to the Services which it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd of you, and the taking of Four Kings hath ſpoke loud enough to be heard of all the World. There are ſome Kings, replyed the inconſiderate <hi>Timur,</hi> that are not ſo eaſily Conquer'd; and if we were one to one, he would perhaps find it hard enough to do what you pretend he hath done. Your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency, reply'd <hi>Zingis</hi> with a Diſdain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Smile, would be no dreadful Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, neither would I uſe any great Precaution to execute upon certain per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that which their Weakneſs doth always render eaſie to be done: But, my Lord, Would you raiſe a War in <hi>Tartary,</hi> after you have ſettled a Peace therein? No, continued <hi>Timur,</hi> with Eyes ſparkling with Fury; becauſe he knew that in the Princeſſe's Preſence my Maſter's Reſpect was an Obſtacle
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:55009:35"/>to his Valour; but I will carry one in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Bowels of the <hi>Monguls,</hi> on the Head of a Hundred thouſand men, when by <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Orders I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain'd an abſolute power over that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt Princeſs. They will oppoſe much leſs than a Hundred thouſand men to your Irruptions; but you will not be the more terrible, and he who hath impos'd Tributes upon the Kings you know of, is able enough to impoſe a heavier Yoke upon the King of <hi>Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This biting Converſation would have come to a greater height, if <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Diſcretion had not obliged him to retire, after he had reſpectfully ſaluted the Princeſs, who looked upon <hi>Timur</hi> with greater Scorn than before. At laſt, Madam, ſaid the Son of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> unto her, You obſerve no more meaſures; your Averſion unto me ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth in all its Extent: but the King your Father, who hath once again pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:55009:36"/>that he will never give you to any other but me, will call you to an account for it. <hi>Timur,</hi> anſwer'd <hi>Taxila</hi> with a reſolute air, Although my Father's Promiſes make you con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain my Inclinations, you ſhall not be the happier for it. You have not labour'd to merit them, and it is not an Inſolency like that which reigneth in your Heart, that can touch the Heart of <hi>Taxila:</hi> and you ſhould have gone to work with ſubmiſſive proceedings, and with a generous and unintereſted Behaviour, and not have relied upon the Queen's Credit; but it is your Fortune you act for, and ſeeing the Crown of <hi>Tartary</hi> hath more power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Charms than mine are, enjoy them, if you can, I will not be jealous, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided you leave me in Repoſe: it's evident enough that my Perſon is not dear unto you; the adventure of <hi>Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſangi</hi> is a ſufficient proof of it, and juſt now you have quarell'd before my
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:55009:36"/>Eyes with a Prince that generouſly ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarded his Life for the preſervation of mine.</p>
               <p>Theſe laſt Words rais'd a cruel Jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie in <hi>Timur</hi>'s Soul: He was already perſwaded that my Maſter lov'd the Princeſs, and now ſaw too plainly that he was alſo belov'd. You have paid very dear for the Obligation of which you ſpeak, replied he, ſeeing that hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Stranger being favour'd by a little good Fortune, hath made himſelf Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of your Heart: but though War and Love do at the ſame time protect him, I hope the King will put a dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference between us that will not be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry advantageous for him. <hi>Timur</hi> then went out and left the Princeſs in liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to meditate upon all that ſhe had cauſe to fear from a man void of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Generosity.</p>
               <p>She was conſidering her Miſery, and <hi>Zingis</hi> was in the ſame Occupati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when <hi>Timur</hi> went to the Queen,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:55009:37"/>and told her all that could animate her both againſt the Princeſs and my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: ſhe gave a favourable Ear to his Complaints, and promis'd ſpeedily to calm all his Troubles. For this end ſhe began to Wheedle her Husband with all thoſe affected Sweetneſſes, that had ſo often ſurpriz'd his Weakneſs; She inform'd him that <hi>Taxila</hi> lov'd <hi>Zingis,</hi> and that contrary to his Word, which ſhe ought to have reſpected, that diſobedient Princeſs thought only of making the Prince of the <hi>Monguls</hi> happy, and eaſily incenſing the Father againſt the Daughter, he proteſted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to her with Oaths, that the rebellious <hi>Taxila</hi> ſhould never be Wife to any but <hi>Timur. Zamar</hi> not content with this firſt Advantage, was deſirous to obtain a ſecond; and ſollicited <hi>Undkan,</hi> that he might humble <hi>Zingis,</hi> to render him his Tributary, as he had done the other Princes that were Vaſſals to their Crown. Seeing this was no eaſie At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:55009:37"/>
                  <hi>Undkan</hi> rejected the Propoſition, and by what he had ſeen the Prince of the <hi>Monguls</hi> do, he believed that no Power was able to conquer him.</p>
               <p>As ſoon as the crafty Queen had left him, he ſent for the Princeſs <hi>Taxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la;</hi> and ſaid unto her, looking ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly upon her, I am unwilling to believe what I have heard concerning you: I am told that your Heart is engag'd, in ſpite of the Choice that I have made for you, and that you prefer the Prince of the <hi>Monguls</hi> to <hi>Timur.</hi> You might have known long ago my Reſolutions in reſpect to your Eſtabliſhment, and you have had leiſure to prepare your Inclinations, if already they were not diſpos'd to obey them. I have deſtin'd you for <hi>Timur</hi> ſince your moſt tender Infancy: He is a King, he is my Wife's Son, and if you have any fooliſh Ideas, reſiſt them, or rather triumph over them, to pleaſe me, ſince no Law ought to be more powerful over you, than
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:55009:38"/>that which obligeth you to obey me. I eſteem <hi>Zingis</hi> as a young Hero, who may aſpire unto great Things: but as to what concerneth you, I can, do no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing for him, having promis'd you un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to another before I knew him.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs heard this Diſcourſe which touched her Repoſe in the moſt ſenſible part, with a great agita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Spirit: She obſerv'd every word of it, and arming her ſelf with a Reſolution worthy of her Vertue, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſhe had a particular Eſteem for <hi>Zingis;</hi> My Lord, anſwered ſhe, The moſt ſevere Judges could not find fault with me, and what he did for me, whilſt <hi>Timur</hi> abandon'd me to a fatal Adventure, doth well deſerve my Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgment. I will not alledge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the important Services which he hath ſo lately render'd to this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, but wilt only tell you, my Lord, That were my Heart abſolutely free, it would never, incline to favour <hi>Timur:</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:55009:38"/>You may Sacrifice me to his Ambiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; my Reſpect oweth all things to you, nevertheleſs my Duty cannot o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vercome my Averſion to <hi>Timur.</hi> Ah, my Lord, There are ſo many Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes in <hi>Aſia,</hi> or ſome other part of the World, able to render his Condition more happy. You are wiſe, interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Undkan,</hi> with a moderation, which ſhortly after degenerated into Violence, and I am perſwaded that you will love <hi>Timur</hi> as ſoon as he ſhall be your Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band: So, <hi>Taxila,</hi> no more words, what I have promiſed, I will and ought to perform.</p>
               <p>In this manner did the King of <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary</hi> diſmiſs his Daughter; She be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moan'd her ſelf, ſhe wept: but all were leagu'd againſt my Maſter, who had none for him, but the Princeſs and <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar;</hi> the Prince of <hi>Brema</hi> having departed from <hi>Cambalu,</hi> at his return from the War, where he had gloriouſly Signaliz'd himſelf, the Cauſe of this his
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:55009:39"/>ſuddain reſolution being unknown.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Axione</hi> an ardent Friend of my Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter's, told him all that had paſt, and the Grief that tormented the Princeſs: This did nothing but ſurcharge him with Affliction, his Love reproaching unto him all the Pains of <hi>Taxila.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zamar</hi> and her haughty Son, being aſſured of <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Paſſion for the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, reſolved upon the concluſion of her Marriage with <hi>Timur:</hi> To delay it, was to ſuffer theſe Fires to grow up, which were but too violent already, ſo that they thought upon nothing elſe.</p>
               <p>The Queen, being ſatisfied with the Promiſe that <hi>Undkan</hi> had made unto her, went to viſit the Princeſs, and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted her with theſe ſad Tidings. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſaid ſhe unto her, with a content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed air, After the Favour which it hath pleaſed the King to grant unto my Son, I cannot too much proclaim his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nor do enough, to teſtifie my Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction: I know that you do not
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:55009:39"/>joyn with me in deſiring that double Alliance with which he honoureth us: but we will make ſo great Efforts to ſoften your Heart, that it will perhaps at laſt become favourable unto us. I ſee a trouble in your Eyes, that promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the continuance of your Scorn; we reſent it with Grief: but, Madam, you ſpend it on conſtant perſons, who will not be wearied with ſuffering. How great need had the Princeſs of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy, not to make a noiſe. I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, Madam, anſwered She, with her ordinary moderation, that you owe only to your ſelf that which you call a Happineſs for <hi>Timur,</hi> and which ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Inclinations that Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven hath given me, can be none for me. Your perpetual Sollicitations force the King to conſtrain me; mean time, Madam, my Reſpect to him exempteth you from the Scorn you ſpeak of, and of which I am not very capable. You know, Madam, that his Alliance exalt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:55009:40"/>you above all the Princeſſes of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and that formerly you could only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend to be rank'd amongſt the meaneſt of them. Muſt this Advantage be made uſe of by you to Sacrifice me? Can I love your Son in ſpite of my Heart; and if I love him not, would you ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us both miſerable? I have told him, and I repeat it unto you, that I will yield up all my Right to the Crown of <hi>Tartary</hi> to him, providing he do not ask of me a Heart, which I have never been able to give him.</p>
               <p>That which was moſt piquant in this Diſcourſe, and which had eſcap'd from the Princeſſe's great Courage did not move <hi>Zamar,</hi> who had had time to prepare her ſelf for all ſhe could ſay. It would be too much, continued ſhe, to abandon your juſt Claim to <hi>Timur;</hi> he is more reaſonable than to expect it: But as he is not without Ambition, and is not ſatisfied with that mean Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure which we have made in the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:55009:40"/>World, ſeeing it is the King's pleaſure, he will ſhare them with you, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect from his own Perſeverance and your Equity, that Heart which you are not yet diſpos'd to give him. For me, Madam, added ſhe, ſaluting her, I will always walk with you as becometh an indulgent and affectionate Mother; and it is no ſmall Token of my Eſteem for you, when I offer you the moſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Thing I have. She went out and left the Princeſs in a Perplexity, which all <hi>Axione</hi>'s Conſolations could not leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen.</p>
               <p>The next Day <hi>Undkan</hi> communica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his moſt conſiderable Subjects, the Deſign he had to make <hi>Timur</hi> his Succeſſor, by giving him the Princeſs his Daughter: The ſincerer ſort, who eſteem'd nothing in <hi>Timur,</hi> becauſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed there was nothing in him that merited their Eſteem, did not approve the Choice: But the unworthy Flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terers whoſe Suffrages <hi>Zamar</hi> had
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:55009:41"/>bought, applauded it, and they made up the greateſt number. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage was publiſhed on the Morrow, and magnificent Preparations were made for it. <hi>Almundzar</hi> was one of thoſe who did not declare for <hi>Timur,</hi> and <hi>Zamar</hi> who lov'd not that Favou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of <hi>Undkan,</hi> put this upon account with her other Motives of hatred againſt him.</p>
               <p>It is impoſſible for me to expreſs my Maſter's Deſpair, when he was told of this ſpeedy Reſolution: He found him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſo much the more miſerable that he could alledge nothing to the King of <hi>Tartary,</hi> but a Love poſteriour to that of <hi>Timur.</hi> He knew that he was lov'd, and taſted the Sweetneſs of that precious Advantage; but he ſaw the lovely <hi>Taxila</hi> made ſubject to an abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute Power, and upon the point to be Sacrific'd to him whom ſhe hated. All his Thoughts were violent: although he ſhould Arm all <hi>Tartary</hi> againſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:55009:41"/>by attempting againſt <hi>Timur</hi>'s Life; he concluded that he had better periſh, than leave him in peaceful Poſſeſſion of <hi>Taxila.</hi> Things were arrived to that height, that the Princeſs was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to ſee him; and this Prohibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion did compleatly incenſe him, ſo that he went out of the Palace reſolv'd to abandon himſelf to his Wrath. Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through the great Place, he ſaw <hi>Timur</hi> accompanied with a ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Attendants, and forgetting that not only he was at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in the view of <hi>Undkan</hi> and <hi>Zamar,</hi> beholding in <hi>Timur</hi> the Perſecutor of <hi>Taxila,</hi> he advanc'd towards him with a terrible air. King of <hi>Tendur,</hi> ſaid he unto him, You who deſign to carry a War as far as the <hi>Mogols,</hi> begin it at <hi>Cambalu</hi> againſt a man, without whoſe Aſſiſtance you would not be in a Condition to exerciſe an unjuſt Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence againſt the Princeſs of <hi>Tartary.</hi> It is by your Orders that I am prohi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bited
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:55009:42"/>to ſee her, and I will loſe my Life, or you ſhall give me Satisfaction for this Injury. <hi>Timur</hi> was not prepar'd for ſo troubleſom a Rencounter, and had no mind to fight: He would have put it off with a diſdainful Anſwer. But <hi>Zingis</hi> who had his Sword drawn in his Hand, conſtrained him to put himſelf in a poſture of Defence. <hi>Timur</hi>'s fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers run in between them: but my Maſter's Valour had quickly diſpers'd them, and ſeeing his unworthy Rival without other Defence than his Arms; Defend thy ſelf, Traytor, ſaid he unto him, and ſhew thy ſelf this Day wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of <hi>Taxila,</hi> by giving ſome Proof of thy Courage. The Son of <hi>Zamar</hi> heard theſe Words, but was no leſs fearful than feeble; and my Maſter ſent him to the Ground pierc'd with ſeveral Stroaks, without receiving any hurt by his Arms.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zingis</hi> would not retire after this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; but <hi>Almundzar,</hi> whom the noiſe
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:55009:42"/>of the Combate had brought to the place, obliged him in the Name of the Princeſs to take care of himſelf, and the Night happily approaching, he made him be conducted unto a ſure Retreat, which I alone knew.</p>
               <p>They carried <hi>Timur</hi> to the Palace, without any ſigns of Life: <hi>Zamar</hi> cry'd out dreadfully, and uttered horrible Imprecations againſt <hi>Taxila</hi> and my Maſter. <hi>Undkan</hi> order'd a diligent Search to be made for them; but <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar</hi> had provided ſufficiently for his Safety. He came to ſee him that very Night, and inform'd him of all the Preparations that were making againſt him, ſhewing him that there was an unavoidable Neceſſity for him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of <hi>Tartary.</hi> My Maſter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted a great while; but <hi>Almundzar</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd him, that though he ſtaid at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balu,</hi> he could not ſee the Princeſs, that ſhe would be in continual Alarms, and that for her quiets-ſake he ought to go &amp; wait
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:55009:43"/>ſomewhere elſe, until this Storm was over-blown. <hi>Zingis</hi> yielded not but upon condition that he ſhould ſee <hi>Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ila</hi> before his Departure, and the next Night the faithful <hi>Almundzar</hi> introduc'd him unto her by a private way which he knew. <hi>Axione</hi> alone was in the Secret: <hi>Almundzar</hi> went out to watch that no body ſhould Surprize them; and <hi>Zingis</hi> caſting himſelf at the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe's Feet, lay there a great while without being able to expreſs himſelf. What have you done, my Lord, ſaid ſhe unto him, raiſing him up? and what will be the Conſequence of this laſt Effect of your Valour? What was I not obliged to do, to take you from <hi>Timur,</hi> Madam, replyed my Maſter, or at leaſt to retard his Happineſs. I know not, continued <hi>Taxila,</hi> whether Heaven may not ſometimes pardon a violent. Action: but certain it is, that I cannot grieve for <hi>Timur</hi>'s preſent Condition. Mean-time, my Lord, you muſt be
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:55009:43"/>gone, you muſt reſolve upon it, for as long as I know you are here, I ſhall be diſquieted with perpetual Frights. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, reply'd my Maſter, If I had only my own Life to look to, I proteſt I would not depart from <hi>Cambalu;</hi> but ſeeing your Quiet is concern'd, I am ready to do any thing. In the mean time, my Princeſs, conſider unto what Puniſhment he that loveth you with ſo much Ardour, is going to be expoſed in the uncertainty of a long Abſence. The proud <hi>Timur</hi> will be cur'd; my Arms have not been ſo happy as to put an end to his life. Ah! who will defend you againſt that Enemy, when <hi>Zingis</hi> is far from you? Suffer me to wait here, until I ſee what may be his De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiny, that ſo I may hinder yours from being miſerable. No, my Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the fair Princeſs, I will not be guilty of ſo cruel a Complaiſance. O Heavens! I tremble as I ſpeak to you, when I conſider that the revengeful <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:55009:44"/>is ſo near us. Suffer me to offer up Vows for you that are not diſturb'd by Fear; perhaps Heaven will hear them: Whatſoever happen, believe that I love you. I do not offend Vertue in aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you of an innocent Tenderneſs, and if this can ſatisfie you, taſte the Pleaſure thereof entirely. Think for your Comfort, when you leave me, that though you depart from <hi>Taxila</hi>'s Preſence, yet you ſhall ſtill abide in her Heart: and that not only her Quiet, but alſo her Reputation obligeth you to this Conſtraint. Yes, Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd the Amorous <hi>Zingis,</hi> I will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, ſince you command me, and I will comfort my ſelf with the precious Aſſurances which your Goodneſs hath given me: But how ſhall I behave my ſelf towards the King your Father? Shall I defend my Life againſt him, if he Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſault me? and will the Reſpect which I owe unto you, permit me to Arm my Subjects againſt the <hi>Tartars?</hi> Yes, my
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:55009:44"/>Lord, anſwered the Generous <hi>Taxila,</hi> and if my Father become your declared Enemy, after the Obligations which he hath unto you, make uſe of your Forces and Valour, only ſpare his Life: It is his Perſon alone that I recommend unto you. Go, my dear <hi>Zingis,</hi> ſtay no longer in a Place ſo full of Danger. At theſe Words ſhe held out her Hand to him, which the Prince reſpectfully Kiſſed, and without hiding her Tears from him, ſhe received his Adieu, and in fine, obliged him to Retire. He took his Leave of <hi>Axione,</hi> who was no leſs Afflicted than the Princeſs; and after he had a thouſand times Embraced <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar,</hi> who had made all neceſſary Preparations for our Departure, we left <hi>Cambalu,</hi> and took the way to <hi>Molg.</hi> Our Voyage was very ſad, and finding the King Dead at our Arrival at <hi>Molg;</hi> my Maſter, who lov'd him tenderly, received a terrible augmentation of Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, and manifeſted the Goodneſs
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:55009:45"/>of his Nature by the deep Mourning in which he continued a great while. His Subjects raviſh'd to ſee him again, Swore an inviolable Fidelity to him; and ſome Months after his Arrival, not doubting but that he would be at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack'd, and <hi>Taxila</hi> having permitted him to defend himſelf, he viſited all his Provinces, &amp; paſt even unto the Deſarts of <hi>Bargu,</hi> and Diſciplin'd in a little time thoſe People, that were never train'd before, teaching them the Art of War which he knew as perfectly as any Prince in the World. His Neighbours jealous of his Glory, would have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed him; but in a few Months time he added ſome Provinces to his Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, amongſt which were <hi>Jek, Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trik,</hi> and <hi>Melair.</hi> In this Triumphant Condition, being more ſenſible of his Love than of ſo much Glory, ſeeing that <hi>Tartary</hi> made no Advances againſt him, and believing that perhaps the face of Affairs there was changed, he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:55009:45"/>a magnificent Embaſſie to <hi>Und<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kan,</hi> to demand the Princeſs, but he was rejected, and treated as a preſumptuous Perſon, <hi>Timur,</hi> as he had foreſeen, was recover'd of his Wounds: He turned the Fury of his Deſpair againſt new E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, and was ever Victorious. But unable to live longer without ſeeing <hi>Taxila,</hi> knowing that ſhe was yet free, by a ſecret Correſpondence which he kept with <hi>Almundzar,</hi> he returned to <hi>Cambalu,</hi> with a Deſign to make the Princeſs conſent to be carried away, or to die before her Eyes, if ſhe proved obſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate. Arriving at the Palace-Gate which was to be opened unto us, the Impatience of <hi>Zingis</hi> betrayed him; he ſpoke, <hi>Zamar</hi> heard him, and you know, my Lord, what ſhe hath done againſt my Maſter.</p>
               <p>THUS ended <hi>Zerbin,</hi> and the King of <hi>Thibet,</hi> after having ſpent ſome time in Admiration of ſo Illuſtrious a Life, aſſur'd the <hi>Mogol</hi> that he had no leſs
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:55009:46"/>Affection for his Maſter, than thoſe that were moſt particularly acquainted with him; and returning to <hi>Almundzar,</hi> prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him for his zealous Fidelity to <hi>Zin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis.</hi> My dear <hi>Almundzar,</hi> ſaid he unto him, What Methods ſhall we take to ſave the Prince <hi>Zingis?</hi> What ſhall we do againſt the cruel <hi>Zamar?</hi> As her Hatred is inflexible, and her Power over <hi>Undkan</hi> abſolute, I ſee no way left to Triumph over her but by Force, and I know not where we can find Forces ſufficient for an Enterprize of that Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance. Whatſoever may happen, continued <hi>Philing,</hi> I will die before I ſuffer the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> to periſh: We muſt ſee <hi>Undkan,</hi> and once more try the ways of Sweetneſs; but if he perſevere in his Cruelty, I will openly declare my ſelf his Enemy. <hi>Almundzar</hi> approved of the generous Reſolution of <hi>Philing,</hi> and aſſured him, that whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he attempted for <hi>Zingis,</hi> he would ſtill ſtand his Friend.</p>
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:55009:46"/>
               <p>This Day paſt over very ſadly; on the Morrow, the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> went to ſee <hi>Undkan,</hi> whom he found ſtill Beleaguer'd by <hi>Zamar,</hi> and made the more haſt, becauſe he feared ſome ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cret Cruelty; for they talked at <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balu</hi> of <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Death, as of a thing ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely certain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zamar</hi> and <hi>Undkan</hi> feared the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of this Prince, who was neither their Subject nor Tributary, and who they ſaw did ever declare himſelf bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for Vertue. His Arrival put them out of Countenance, and <hi>Zamar</hi> was extreamly troubled at it: My Lord, ſaid he to the King of <hi>Tartary,</hi> I don't know whether the Deſign that hath brought me hither this Morning, will have a favourable Succeſs; but I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt I never had a more preſſing Intereſt, than that which I have in the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> Life. It will be glorious unto you, my Lord, to Treat a Prince generouſly, who you believe hath given
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:55009:47"/>you juſt cauſe of Offence: but it would be an eternal Shame unto you, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe an unjuſt Cruelty over him, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo many Reaſons to eſteem him, and to look upon him as the Greateſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong Men. No body is ignorant of the Services that he hath done you, and his Love for the Princeſs is the onely Crime you can accuſe him of. But, my Lord, In the Dignity to which Heaven hath exalted you, conſider what you owe to that of other Kings: Shall you be Powerful only to be Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, and will you exerciſe that Power over an Enemy, who would not be in your Hands, but that he put himſelf in them; an Enemy all whoſe Steps are Glorious, and on whom the Eyes of innumerable Kingdoms are fix'd: that would be a ready way to confirm the Ideas which other Nations have of us: they look upon us ſtill as <hi>Scythians;</hi> that is to ſay, People without Laws, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Gods, and without Religion. Will
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:55009:47"/>you imitate thoſe barbarous Examples of Antiquity, which are deſervedly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem'd frightful Prodigies? And will you Sacrifice a great King for ſo light Reaſons? Theſe light Reaſons, inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted <hi>Zamar,</hi> tranſported with Anger, will not paſs for ſuch in the Hearts of Mothers, as tender as I am, and he who attempted to kill my Son before my Eyes, and almoſt in my Arms, can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be too ſeverely puniſhed for a Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence that hath coſt him ſo much Blood, and me ſo many Tears.</p>
               <p>I am told, reply'd the King of <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi> that <hi>Timur</hi> was well accompany'd, when <hi>Zingis</hi> attack'd him, and even that the Rules of Generoſity were not at all obſerv'd on this Occaſion, ſeeing many Swords were at once turn'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt one Man: And methinks I have alſo heard, that the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> ſaved the King of <hi>Tendur</hi>'s Life oftner than once in the Wars of <hi>Ung.</hi> My Lord, anſwered <hi>Zamar,</hi> You are ſo well
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:55009:48"/>inform'd of all that concerns <hi>Zingis,</hi> that it ſeems you have kept a particular Correſpondence with him; and that doubtleſs in our Dominions, and upon theſe Conjectures, we might juſtly—What, Madam, interrupted <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> coldly, Lay me in Chains as well as him, and add one Injuſtice to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other? 'Tis no matter from what Mouth I have learn'd the Miracles of his Life; it's ſufficient that I am a very ſincere and zealous Admirer of them. My Lord, ſaid <hi>Unkan,</hi> The Queen ſpeaketh as an enraged Mother, and you ought not to condemn her Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. I have conſidered your Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, but they have not convinced me; and it would be no leſs than to endan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Vertue, to ſuffer theſe Men to live that diſquiet Kingdoms, and without Reaſon defile the Palaces of Princes with Blood. I have received Services of <hi>Zingis,</hi> and Honour'd him as a Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger whom I judged worthy of my E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem;
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:55009:48"/>but he, abuſing my Eaſineſs, remain'd at my Court, to delude a young Princeſs, and withdraw her from the Obedience which ſhe oweth unto me; and puſhing on his Arrogancy to a greater height, he aſſaulteth a Prince who is my Son, becauſe he is my Wife's, and to whom I have deſtin'd my Daughter; and returneth <hi>incognito</hi> to <hi>Cambalu,</hi> to be introduc'd into my Houſe, there to Plot ſecretly with the weak <hi>Taxila.</hi> What do I know but he hath laid Deſigns againſt my Life, and who will aſſure me of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency of his Intentions? In fine, I owe this Victim to my own quiet, and it's only to loſe time in vain to ſollicite his Liberty. I perceive, my Lord, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd <hi>Philing,</hi> That his Ruin is ſworn, and that you cannot be oppos'd in pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces entirely ſubject to your Power. But of the Humour of which I am, I will never ſuffer this Cruelty without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting it. Probably you never fear
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:55009:49"/>the Wrath of Heaven, nor the Scorn of Men: but do you imagine that the juſter part of this Portion of the World which we inhabit, will ſuffer you to immolate the Illuſtrious <hi>Zingis,</hi> without doing any thing for his Revenge? <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, Perſia,</hi> and <hi>China</hi> will be eaſily mov'd, and there wants only, added he, inſpir'd by his Generoſity, a Prince ſuch as I am to excite them to it, and to bring into your Dominions a Storm that will ſoon overwhelm you. He went out after this, and ſeeing his Threats were far diſtant, <hi>Undkan</hi> and <hi>Zamar</hi> were more incens'd than fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned at them. Their firſt Thought was to make him to be apprehended; but <hi>Almundzar,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Tartars</hi> in whom <hi>Undkan</hi> put Confidence, hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him from proceeding to that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremity, repreſenting unto him, that it would be to arm all the Powers of the Univerſe againſt himſelf. <hi>Zamar</hi> was not of this Opinion, but ſhe was forc'd to yield.</p>
               <pb n="93" facs="tcp:55009:49"/>
               <p>The King of <hi>Thibet</hi> would once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain endeavour to ſee the Princeſs: He was denied admittance into her Apart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as formerly; but whilſt incens'd with this Denial, he meditated upon Means to humble an unjuſt Power, the afflicted <hi>Taxila</hi> and amiable <hi>Axione</hi> lived in a ſad Solitarineſs, and were on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly accompanied with diſmal Thoughts. But what were the Thoughts of <hi>Zingis,</hi> ſo nigh <hi>Taxila,</hi> and yet ſo unable to diſcourſe with her? Knowing his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies ſo well, he doubted not of his Miſery; and the Idea of Death, which he had ſo often brav'd, was leſs tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting to him, than his Abſence from the Princeſs.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Almundzar</hi> intereſt'd himſelf as a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Friend in <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Misfortunes: But how great ſoever his Credit was with <hi>Undkan, Zamar</hi> ſtill got the better of him. He ſpoke boldly enough, to make himſelf be prohibited to ſpeak more; and he had not ſo much as the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:55009:50"/>Conſolation to be able to mitigate the Incommodities which the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> ſuffered in Priſon. <hi>Zerbin</hi> who ſtill lay hid in the Houſe of <hi>Zingis</hi>'s ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous Friend, inform'd him, that his Maſter had Six hundred of the braveſt Men in the World hid in ſeveral places about <hi>Cambalu,</hi> who would chearfully expoſe themſelves for their Prince. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar</hi> reſolved immediately to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate theſe News to the King of <hi>Thibet,</hi> and was glad to ſee a Party en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe, whereof that Prince might be Head.</p>
               <p>There were even <hi>Tartars</hi> bold e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to declare in <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Timur,</hi> whom they hated mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tally, and whoſe Rule they dreaded. <hi>Almundzar</hi> thought fit to hide his Zeal, that he might be more uſeful to the Princeſs and the King of the <hi>Mogols,</hi> and by this Policy he had the liberty to Negotiate with a great many conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able <hi>Tartars,</hi> who reſpected the Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:55009:50"/>of <hi>Zingis,</hi> and contemned the baſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of <hi>Timur,</hi> both which had appeared in ſo many Occaſions.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Thibet,</hi> enrag'd with the ſecond Denial he had received from the Princeſs's Guards, carried his Vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion along with him to <hi>Almundzar</hi>'s houſe, to whom he made his complaints. You ſee, my Lord, anſwer'd the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> that all Things here are carried on againſt Honour and Juſtice; neither do I believe that in any other they would fail in the Reſpect that is due to a King, ſuch as you are. My dear <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar,</hi> ſaid <hi>Philing,</hi> I would not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps much reſent Things of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if I had only intereſts of Glory to look to; but I have thoſe of a Lover to ſatisfie, and in me you behold the moſt Amorous of all Men. Of whom, my Lord, reply'd the aſtoniſh'd <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar?</hi> of <hi>Axione,</hi> continued <hi>Philing,</hi> of that charming Damſel that is ſo dear unto the Princeſs, whom I have lov'd
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:55009:51"/>theſe ſeveral years, and whom I will love Eternally. I know not, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you have frequented her enough to know all her Vertue, which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed equal to her Beauty; and the obſcurity of her Birth is recompenſed by the Greatneſs of her Thoughts. This Effect of <hi>Axione</hi>'s Merit doth not at all ſurprize me, added <hi>Almundzar,</hi> but that which aſtoniſheth me, is, the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner in which ſhe came to <hi>Cambalu,</hi> and the abode ſhe hath made here without you. It is nevertheleſs ſhe alone that brought me hither, anſwered <hi>Philing,</hi> and for whoſe ſake I have ſtaid ſo long here. But, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> I muſt make you perfectly acquainted with ſo rare a Perſon, and the Paſſion that I have for her, in opening my Heart ſincerely to you. <hi>Almundzar</hi> who was very deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to know <hi>Philing</hi>'s adventures, pray'd him not to defer this Pleaſure, and the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> who could not be more agreeably buſied, than in ſpeaking of <hi>Axione,</hi> did thus begin his Relation.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:55009:51"/>
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>PHILING</hi> and <hi>AXIONE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THE King of <hi>Thibet</hi> is none of the leaſt conſiderable of <hi>Aſia,</hi> whether you conſider its Extent or Commerce: For though it be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded with Mountains, the <hi>Indians</hi> and <hi>Chinois</hi> do often viſit us. Our Towns are well Peopled, our Fields Fertil, and Magnificence is no ſtranger amongſt us.</p>
               <p>I was but Six Years Old when I loſt my Father, and Nine when the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs <hi>Thamiriza</hi> my Siſter and I were alſo left deſtitute of our Mother. Theſe firſt Misfortunes were great, but our Age diminiſh'd our Sorrows, and made us quickly forget them. It would even be hard to tell you what we felt, and I confeſs that I have but a ſlight Remembrance of theſe my deareſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations</p>
               <pb n="98" facs="tcp:55009:52"/>
               <p>My Father had been entirely belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved of his Subjects, and his Memory was ſtill dear unto them: Never per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps was there ſeen a People more faithful to a young Succeſſour, who neither knew his Fortune, nor what might diſturb it.</p>
               <p>Among all thoſe whom my Father had diſtinguiſh'd by his Favour, <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezar</hi> was the moſt powerful. There were even Alliances betwixt the Royal Family and his, and to him the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gency was committed during my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancy. He acquitted himſelf worthily of this Charge: His knowledge was vaſt, and his Courage great; He was Vigilant and Zealous, and the Face of Affairs was not chang'd under his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct. For me, I had Governours of great Merit, and <hi>Thamiriza</hi> had cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen Women to wait upon her.</p>
               <p>Our ordinary Reſidence was at <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen: Hildezar</hi> lodg'd in the Palace; He had loſt his Wiſe, who left him
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:55009:52"/>one onely Daughter, who was Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with no leſs Care than my Siſter; and they placed about me ſeveral young Children of Noble Families, to render my Childiſh Occupations more agreeable to me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hildezar</hi> at that time was but 35 Years Old: He was not free of Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and ſeeing he had all the Power of <hi>Thibet</hi> in his Hands, he reſolved to make me marry his Daughter. Hunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing was his beloved and moſt frequent Divertiſement; His Family was more numerous than mine, his Expences much greater, and his Train equally Splendid. 'Tis true, that one of Ten Years of Age requir'd no great Magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficence, and it's as certain that my In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts were not neglected by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent. He had for one Year been poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of all Authority in <hi>Thibet</hi> under my Name, by the Death of the Queen my Mother, and our Mourning being o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, Divertiſements ſhar'd our Time
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:55009:53"/>with Exerciſes proper to form both the Body and Mind. All our Mountains are of very difficult acceſs; there is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs very good Game, and <hi>Hil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dezar</hi> who often Diverted himſelf with Hunting, ſuffer'd me ſometimes to take a part, without expoſing me to what is laborious in that Exerciſe.</p>
               <p>Having pick'd out one of the faireſt Daies of the Spring, we went to one of the pleaſanteſt Places that we could light upon, near <hi>Kachen,</hi> and travers'd the Hills a great while with greater Vigour than is uſual in Children: Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing under ſome ſcatter'd Trees, whoſe Roots are bath'd with a ſmall Rivulet, we ſaw a Spectacle that ſurpriz'd my young Heart, and made a laſting Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion upon it. The Brook was ſwell'd with the Blood of many dead and dying Men, and a few paces off, we beheld a Girl of Six or Seven Years of Age, richly habited, and of a Beauty ſo extraordinary, that it aſtoniſh'd all
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:55009:53"/>our Troop. She was weeping, and lifted up her Eies and Hands, not knowing from whom to ask Help. In this lamentable Condition, her Clothes were even ſtain'd with Blood, and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver could an Object more charming and more worthy of Compaſſion pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it ſelf before us. <hi>Hildezar</hi> ſtopp'd; our Arrival made the Innocent Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known redouble her Cries, and fright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with her Misfortune, ſhe threw herſelf among our Horſes-feet. I muſt acknowledge, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> that Love ſeiz'd upon me from that very mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but I did not perceive it at firſt, and my Innocence made me miſtake it for ſimple Compaſſion. <hi>Hildezar</hi> alighted from his Horſe, and approacht the amiable Stranger: He is dead, ſaid ſhe, with a charming Innocency, in the <hi>Tartarian Language,</hi> but ſomewhat dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent from ours, My Father is dead: Theſe cruel Ones have kill'd him, but he hath kill'd ſome of them alſo. Ah,
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:55009:54"/>my Father, added ſhe! turning her head towards the dead Bodies: Ah, my Father! I ſhall never ſee you more, and will die with you. <hi>Hildezar</hi> ſtruck with Compaſſion took her in his Arms, and made her ſhew him whom ſhe cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led her Father; but neither in him nor the reſt could we perceive any ſign of Life.</p>
               <p>After this, <hi>Hildezar</hi> himſelf carried the little <hi>Axione,</hi> for ſo ſhe was call'd, to <hi>Kachen,</hi> asking Queſtions of her by the way; and all he learn'd was that <hi>Marzillus</hi> her Father, with thoſe that accompanied him, had been attack'd in that place by theſe wicked Men; but ſhe could neither inform him of her Country nor Quality, which, in all probability, was not mean. The ſight of my Siſter, and of <hi>Alzine Hildezar</hi>'s Daughter, who were both almoſt of an Age with <hi>Axione,</hi> did a little calm her Sorrow, and in a little time ſhe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear'd ſo Fair, that all our Court was
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:55009:54"/>Charm'd with her. I never ſaw ſo much Grace, Sweetneſs and Modeſty, as appear'd in the meaneſt of her Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; and though ſhe had paſt her firſt Years in a Vagrant Life, ſhe had an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirable Genius, which was not cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted by the Defects of her Educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: Her Reaſon out-running her Years, did much ſurpaſs that of perſons that had attain'd to a much greater Age: She was Complaiſant, without doing any thing that was mean, and obſerv'd a certain deference to the Quality of a King, which my Tenderneſs could not endure. My Siſter lov'd her perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Axione</hi> liv'd familiarly with her, and we paſt the ſpace of Five or Six Years with the greateſt Sweetneſs in the World. Mean-time, <hi>Axione</hi> became ſo Fair, and I ſo Amorous, that I thought on nothing elſe but to See and Pleaſe her; I render'd unto her ſome little Services that engaged her Acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledgment: but being ever Humble
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:55009:55"/>and Modeſt, ſhe received them with Reſpects that my Paſſion could not away with. <hi>Axione,</hi> ſaid I unto her one Day, after I had preſented her with ſome Flowers, for which ſhe returned as many Thanks, as if the Gift had been much more precious; you value ſorry Preſents at a very High Rate, but I can offer ſome unto you that are more worthy to be regarded. All that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth from your Hand, my Lord, replied ſhe, ought to be very conſiderable unto me, and a King ſuch as you are, can never give ſorry Preſents to a Girl like me. <hi>Axione,</hi> cried I out, If ſome Flowers have obtained for me ſo obliging an Anſwer, what may I not expect from a Heart that is leſs unworthy of you, which I have given you a great while ago? Hitherto my Eies alone have told you of it, but I muſt now let you know it in another manner. Yes, <hi>Axione,</hi> I have given you that tender Heart which will prove faithful to you; and
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:55009:55"/>if you are capable of Acknowledgment, it muſt be for this Preſent. The mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt <hi>Axione</hi> bluſh'd, ſigh'd, and look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon me with a touching air, but full of Grandeur and Majeſty, the Hearts of Soveraigns ought not to ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der themſelves ſo eaſily, my Lord, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied ſhe, nor ſhould they be received with ſo little Precaution. Think upon what you were Born, and remember the Condition in which you found me; reflect ſeriouſly upon a Goodneſs that may paſs for Weakneſs, and which I will not abuſe; believe that I will ever reſpect in you the Dignity of a King, and a Merit, which perhaps, I am too ſenſible of. But, my Lord, believe alſo that the obſcurity of my Life doth not vex me ſo much, as to make me deſire to get rid of it by crafty Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods. You have too much Wit, <hi>Axione,</hi> anſwer'd I, and would to Heaven, that you had as much Tenderneſs! What can the Obſcurity of your Birth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:55009:56"/>againſt ſo much Beauty and Vertue that are in you? D'ye believe that I am one of thoſe that alwaies offer Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifices to Fortune, and never to true Merit; <hi>I</hi> am contented with what <hi>I</hi> have, and would eſteem my ſelf more happy in pleaſing you, than in being lov'd of the Greateſt Queen in the World. Do not then preſcribe Leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons unto me, which I eſteem Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; ſuffer me to love you, and ſuffer it with pleaſure: But all my Earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs was to no purpoſe, ſhe ſtill an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd as before; and all the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage I had was to ſpeak, and to be heard, and when <hi>I</hi> proteſted unto her that it was not the Quality of a King that embolden'd me to take this liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſhe ſeem'd better ſatisfi'd: but <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar,</hi> when her Stature was form'd, and her Beauty compleat, <hi>I</hi> felt my Paſſion augmented, and found my ſelf capable to ſacrifice all for her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I</hi> was not the only perſon that lov'd
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:55009:56"/>her in this manner; <hi>I</hi> had a terrible Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>val. <hi>Hildezar</hi> Regent of <hi>Thibet,</hi> of an advanc'd Age, <hi>Alzine</hi>'s Father, who had acquir'd a great deal of Eſteem in our Country, and amongſt our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, by his prudent Conduct, ſeeing the fair and vertuous <hi>Axione</hi> grow up, felt his Heart ſeiz'd upon by Flames of an extraordinary Violence: He la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd in vain to extinguiſh them, and that which he had done for <hi>Axione</hi> flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering his Hope, he ſuffer'd a Malady to gather ſtrength, which it was not poſſible for him to cure.</p>
               <p>He had remark'd by all my Actions the Love that <hi>I</hi> had for <hi>Axione;</hi> but he did not believe it ſo pure, and imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning that a young King cannot be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Ambition, he hop'd that Time would fix my Inclinations on ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Object, and ſuffer'd his own to act freely.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Axione</hi> had look'd upon him as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, ſent unto her by Heaven, and
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:55009:57"/>whatſoever he did, ſhe thought on no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſs than what he truly deſign'd.</p>
               <p>One Day when <hi>I</hi> was not in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, <hi>Hildezar</hi> found <hi>Axione</hi> walking alone upon a Terrace, and making uſe of this Opportunity, when there was none to obſerve him. Stay, <hi>Axione,</hi> ſaid he unto her, <hi>I</hi> have a Buſineſs of Importance to impart unto you: <hi>Axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one,</hi> who did not foreſee what was to follow, ſmil'd at thoſe words. What is it, my Lord, replied ſhe? Is it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Obligations that <hi>I</hi> have un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, and would you chide me for having fail'd in any thing <hi>I</hi> owe unto you? If you have any Obligation unto me, anſwer'd <hi>Hildezar,</hi> it is in your power eaſily to acquit your ſelf of it, and it is this power which is yet un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known you, that <hi>I</hi> would inform you of. As long as you were a Child, not feeling what <hi>I</hi> now feel with the ſame Violence, <hi>I</hi> abſtain'd from telling you what was then above your Reaſon, and
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:55009:57"/>
                  <hi>I</hi> have ſince been reſtrain'd by a Fear, which a more abſolute Power enableth me now to ſurmount. One that loves deſperately cannot remain alwaies diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet and reſerv'd. This Declaration will ſurprize you: but, <hi>Axione,</hi> the knowledge you have of your own Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ought to have prepar'd you for it. Fear nothing from my Deſigns, they are full of Reſpect, and at the ſame time that <hi>I</hi> offer unto you my Heart, with an abſolute Empire over my Will, <hi>I</hi> offer unto you alſo my Hand, and all that Fortune hath given me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hildezar</hi>'s Diſcourſe ſtruck <hi>Axione</hi> dumb: He ſollicited her long for an Anſwer, before ſhe was able to return one; at laſt recovering a little out of the Trouble which ſo unexpected a piece of News had caus'd in her; Is it poſſible, my Lord, anſwer'd ſhe, that what you told me, is not of purpoſe to try me, and can there be any Truth in a Diſcourſe of that nature? Can you
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:55009:58"/>doubt of it, replied <hi>Hildezar,</hi> and can you ſuſpect one of my Age of ſuch Tricks? My Love to you muſt be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ardent, ſeeing no Conſideration can reſtrain me from declaring it. O, my Lord! cried out <hi>Axione,</hi> Wherein have <hi>I</hi> ſinn'd againſt Heaven, that it ſhould expoſe me to ſuch a Misfortune? What! is this Misfortune ſo great, anſwer'd <hi>Hildezar,</hi> that you ſhould be ſo much afflicted with it? Yes, my Lord, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded ſhe, It is one of the moſt cruel Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes that could befal me; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the Obligations that <hi>I</hi> have unto you, <hi>I</hi> would for ever abhor my ſelf if <hi>I</hi> ſhould contribute to diſtain your Glory. What would not people ſay, if You ſuffer'd Your ſelf to fall in an Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, which the greeneſt Youth cannot render excuſable? What Honour could my Alliance do unto You? Unknown to my Self and to all the World, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps of baſe Blood and unworthy of Your Inclinations. <hi>Axione</hi> interrupted
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:55009:58"/>
                  <hi>Hildezar,</hi> That Modeſty doth ſo ſet off the Luſtre of Your Vertue, that it would augment my Love, if it was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of any Augmentation: <hi>I</hi> ſee in You all that can ſatisfie my Ambition and Tenderneſs. Speak then poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Well then, <hi>Hildezar</hi> continu'd ſhe, <hi>I</hi> muſt be ſincere ſeeing You deſire it, and <hi>I</hi> muſt tell You, that this unknown Blood that ſwelleth my Veins inſpireth me with ſo Noble Sentiments, that <hi>I</hi> will never do any thing until <hi>I</hi> be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of my Birth. <hi>I</hi> feel it much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than perhaps <hi>I</hi> ſhall ever know it. — It is not that which determineth You, interrupted <hi>Hildezar,</hi> and <hi>I</hi> owe unto another Cauſe that Reſiſtance which filleth me with Deſpair. <hi>I</hi> am neither Young, nor a King: But, <hi>Axi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one, I</hi> love You, and am able to make You very Happy? <hi>I</hi> have Power, do not conſtrain me to have Recourſe to it. <hi>Philing</hi> is a Soveraign, but his Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity obligeth him to a great Alliance;
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:55009:59"/>He amuſeth You only with a fleeting Paſſion, for Love is much more ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liv'd in the Hearts of Kings, than of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men. I leave you, and wholly depend upon your Anſwer, asking no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of you but what is reaſonable: He retir'd, and <hi>Axione</hi> remain'd alone, in liberty to reflect upon what ſhe had heard. This Diſcourſe made ſuch an impreſſion upon her Countenance, that it was eaſily perceiv'd, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Care that ſhe took to compoſe her ſelf. I found her vex'd, full of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraction; and in fine, in a condition that I have never before ſeen her in. What aileth you this Morning, <hi>Axione,</hi> ſaid I unto her, You are no more Your ſelf, and I cannot imagine the Cauſe of this Change. My Words rouſed her up a little; ſhe aſſur'd me that nothing extraordinary had befaln her; but I read too well in her Eies, whom Love had made me ſtudy many Years, to be contented with this Anſwer. You
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:55009:59"/>are not ſincere, continued I; but if You hide any thing from the tender In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt that <hi>I</hi> take in You, You will be the moſt cruel Perſon in the World. My Lord, replied <hi>Axione, I</hi> ought not to ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie You in what you ask of me; ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs <hi>I</hi> perceive, <hi>I</hi> ſhall not be able to conceal it from You, but upon condition to moderate Your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment. Know then, my Lord, that this <hi>Hildezar,</hi> whom Heaven hath made an Inſtrument to ſweeten the firſt Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of my Life, hath now done me the moſt ſenſible of all Injuries: There needed no more to make me compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend <hi>Hildezar</hi>'s Deſigns; and had it not been for the condition under which <hi>Axione</hi> made me her Confident, <hi>I</hi> would have made ſearch for him to puniſh him. <hi>Hildezar</hi> is in love with You, replied <hi>I,</hi> and what will become of me, <hi>Axione,</hi> if You be favourable unto him? My Heart, added that fair Girl, is not very precious; but it is not to <hi>Hildezar</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:55009:60"/>that my Inclinations have deſtin'd it. <hi>I</hi> am expos'd to his Diſcourſes, and perhaps to his Humours — What? D'ye make no reckoning of my Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, interrupted <hi>I?</hi> Dy'e think that my Love will ſuffer his to act in quiet? O my dear <hi>Axione!</hi> my Intereſt in this is greater than Yours; and You are too dear unto me, to ſuffer You to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portun'd by a Rival; <hi>I</hi> am a King, and ought to be Maſter of all but <hi>Axione.</hi> You may extend your Dominion even over my Will, my Lord, replied ſhe, ſeeing Your Generoſity will never put upon me any thing that is rude; and beſides, You are All Potent here. No, <hi>Axione,</hi> added <hi>I, I</hi> will never aſſume any Power where You are, but what You are pleas'd to allow me, for You ſhall alwaies Reign Soveraignly over me. Oh Heaven, continued that amiable Maid! Can it be poſſible that <hi>I</hi> ſhould prove ungrateful to ſo much Goodneſs, and will You not one Day enable me
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:55009:60"/>to teſtifie my Acknowledgment? <hi>I</hi> hope, my Lord, continued ſhe, That my Indifferency, or rather Diſdain qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing <hi>Hildezar</hi>'s Hopes, he will change his manner of acting; but if it fall out otherwiſe, <hi>I</hi> muſt change mine. Yes, <hi>Axione,</hi> replied <hi>I,</hi> and beſides You muſt change Your Condition: Do not think that <hi>I</hi> will ſtick to make You Queen of <hi>Thibet:</hi> The Throne that <hi>I</hi> poſſeſs will never pleaſe Me without You; and if our Laws did permit me, <hi>I</hi> would offer it unto You without a Partner. My Lord, anſwered <hi>Axione,</hi> with Looks full of Gratitude, You ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour too much a miſerable Unknown, whom Fortune hath hitherto eſteem'd unworthy of the leaſt of her Favours. It would indeed be a very great One to poſſeſs the Affections of an Illuſtrious Prince, and to ſhare his Crown with him: But, my Lord, <hi>I</hi> will never a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe ſo generous a Bounty; Your Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall never be ſoil'd with an Alli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:55009:61"/>like mine, and to prevent that Misfortune, <hi>I</hi> would abandon my ſelf to the moſt cruel Miſeries, and even give my ſelf to <hi>Hildezar.</hi> What! ſhall it be ſaid, that <hi>Axione</hi> is Queen of <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi> and that all her Dowry is a Deſcent unknown to all the World? <hi>I</hi> owe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to You, and <hi>I</hi> owe alſo to my. Self a perfect Manifeſtation of what <hi>I</hi> am; and if there be found, added ſhe, with an extraordinary Majeſty, any thing in my Life that is not unworthy of You, believe me, my Lord, there ſhall none be able to diſpute it with You, and <hi>I</hi> would eſteem my ſelf too happy.</p>
               <p>O Heaven, cried <hi>I</hi> out, charm'd with <hi>Axione</hi>'s Vertue! Could you have infus'd ſo Noble a Grandeur into an ordinary perſon? Ah, Madam! do not ſeek for any other Proof of what You are, than the Beauty of Your Senti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: They render You worthy of all the Thrones of the World; Accept of mine, and do not torment me by too
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:55009:61"/>modeſt and obſtinate a Denial. My Lord, replied ſhe, with a ſtronger Tone, It is an unalterable Reſolution: <hi>I</hi> cannot tell whether <hi>I</hi> commit a Crime againſt Decency, when <hi>I</hi> confeſs unto You, that You have touch'd my Heart, and that of all that my Eies can be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, nothing can be more agreeable to them than You; but <hi>I</hi> will willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly commit this Fault, to teſtifie unto You, that the dearer You are unto me, and the more highly <hi>I</hi> eſteem You, the greater Care <hi>I</hi> ought to have of Your Glory. She bluſh'd in finiſhing theſe laſt Words, and would by no means continue the Diſcourſe.</p>
               <p>To ſatisfie her, <hi>I</hi> was conſtrain'd to neglect the Offence that ſhe had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved from <hi>Hildezar,</hi> and to act as if <hi>I</hi> had never been inform'd of it. But my Eies being then opened, <hi>I</hi> ſaw but too well what paſt in the Heart of this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous Rival: But <hi>I</hi> did not pene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trate ſo well the Factions that he was
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:55009:62"/>raiſing in <hi>Thibet,</hi> by the Authority he had acquir'd during my Infancy. Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoon as he had diſcover'd his Thoughts to <hi>Axione,</hi> he took ſecret meaſures to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lige me to Marry his Daughter, on whom <hi>I</hi> had never ſo much as thought, and of whom he never ſpoke to me. He engag'd all the Kingdom, and ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing till then my Education and Love had occupi'd me more than State-Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, it was eaſie for him to inſinuate into thoſe who ſhar'd the Publick Cares with him, all that he was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous they ſhould do. He told to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry remarkable perſon that had Credit among the People, That <hi>I,</hi> poſſeſt with a blind Obſtinacy, abandon'd my ſelf to the Love of the unknown <hi>Axione,</hi> and that I deſign'd no other Princeſs for my Subjects. Every one deſir'd him to ſpeak to me of it, condemning my Pre-occupation; but he refus'd to do it, and others were oblig'd to undertake the Buſineſs.</p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:55009:62"/>
               <p>I did not at all ſuſpect what their Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupation at that time was, and was much ſurpriz'd one Day, being upon the account of an Affair of great Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance, oblig'd to be preſent at Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, to which I ſeldom went, believing that my Preſence was not alwaies ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, when the moſt Venerable of thoſe that compos'd this Aſſembly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs'd himſelf to me in theſe Terms:</p>
               <p>I ſpeak unto you in the Name of all Your Subjects, my Lord, who entreat You by my Mouth to give them a Queen. Your Age is not far advanc'd, but Your Reaſon is; and this will tell You, that nothing can be more agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to People, than to ſee their Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns in a Condition to leave behind them a Glorious Poſterity. This ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth the King more Vigilant, and the Subjects better Diſciplin'd. Unmarry'd Princes are for the moſt part without Intereſt, and that of a Family, engageth them to labour for the Glory, and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grandizing
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:55009:63"/>of Your Dominions. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve then, my Lord, to ſatisfie us, and do as ſeveral of Your Predeceſſors have done. Go not to bring from a Foreign Clime a Princeſs that could not prove very affectionate unto us. There are in <hi>Thibet</hi> Houſes Noble enough to aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire unto the Alliance of their King: And even that Favour is due unto the Zeal and Loyalty of <hi>Hildezar. Alzine</hi> is able to reckon Princes amongſt her Anceſtors, and is not the firſt of her Blood that hath enter'd into the Royal Family of <hi>Thibet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This Harangue aſtoniſh'd me to ſuch a degree, that I was at firſt unable to make any Anſwer. Choler ſeiz'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on my Soul, and I look'd upon theſe Men as ſo many Enemies, plotting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my Quiet, and I was particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly incens'd againſt <hi>Hildezar,</hi> not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that he was the only Cauſe of all that paſs'd. In the end, compoſing my Countenance, which the Politick
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:55009:63"/>
                  <hi>Hildezar</hi> examin'd, I ſpoke, becauſe I was oblig'd ſo to do. <hi>Botſar,</hi> ſaid I to him that had expreſs'd himſelf in the Words I have related unto you, I don't know from whom you have immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately receiv'd the Commiſſion of which you have at preſent acquitted your ſelf: but I aſſure you it is not at all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to me. Who ought to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt themſelves more than mine own Heart in the Choice you deſire me to make? and what man ſhould be more careful of my Fortune than my ſelf? You muſt needs look upon me as a weak Perſon, when you take the boldneſs to preſcribe Rules to me, and determine the Objects of my Inclinations. I am neither ſo ignorant of the Laws of <hi>Thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bet,</hi> nor of thoſe of all the other King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms of the World, but that I can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulate my Actions with ſome Glory, and am able to chooſe a Wife for my ſelf when it ſhall be time. My Lord, ſaid <hi>Hildezar,</hi> ſeeing that I had leſt off
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:55009:64"/>ſpeaking, you muſt not take it ill, if ſo many perſons who look upon you as their only Good, do ardently deſire to ſee you tied unto them by the Intereſt of which you ſpeak. I have perhaps given them my Suffrage; but it was not I that propos'd <hi>Alzine,</hi> though, my Lord, ſhe may well countervail an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known Maid, and would be more a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable to your Subjects. <hi>Hildezar,</hi> interrupted I with a wrathful Look, You abuſe the Conſideration that I have for you: I am nevertheleſs clear-ſighted enough to perceive that you are not ſo void of Eſteem for unknown Perſons; and you alſo might have ſeen enough of my Inclinations, to have made you more reſpectful and leſs daring. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over, I am a King, and pretend to be Maſter. When the People of <hi>Thibet</hi> are Oppreſt by my Injuſtice, it will be time for them then to complain againſt me; when I ſhall abandon them to their Enemies, then will they have
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:55009:64"/>cauſe to upbraid me with Baſeneſs; but hitherto they can charge me with no Fault, but I may juſtly reproach all of you, that you have fail'd in that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, which I will endeavour to make you obſerve in time to come. After this I went out full of Wrath, the Ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects whereof I would have made theſe preſumptuous Ones feel, but that I was afraid to give <hi>Axione</hi> the leaſt cauſe of Offence. She read the Agitation of my Mind in my Eies, but I was not willing to inform her of the true Cauſe thereof, diſguiſing it with ſome other pretext.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Hildezar</hi> being incens'd againſt me for the intereſt of his Daughter, but much more for that of his Love, a dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Malice ſucceeded in the place of the Affection that he had hitherto pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt unto me: He eſteem'd my Ruine neceſſary for the eſtabliſhment of his Repoſe and Fortune; and ſeeing the Peace that reign'd among us, ſuffer'd
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:55009:65"/>no Cloud to hang over us; he rais'd a War by pernicious Intrigues, not doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing but that I would run with Ardour unto the Places where I might acquire any Glory. He hop'd by my Death to aſcend a Throne that had no other Heirs; and though <hi>Benzide</hi> and <hi>Othrize,</hi> two conſiderable Princes in <hi>Thibet,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended ſome Right to it, yet the Suffra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges he was aſſur'd of made him look upon them as no great Obſtacle to his Deſigns. It was he then that wheedled that part of my Subjects into an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, who inhabit the Frontiers towards <hi>India.</hi> Upon the firſt noiſe of this Rebellion, I reſolv'd to act the part of a Captain and King. <hi>Hildezar</hi> was cold and ſlow, and did not appear ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry forward in preparing for the War: His Creatures imitated him, but in ſpite of him, I ſaw my ſelf very quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly at the head of a conſiderable Army. Aſſoon as he ſaw me ready to be gone, he counterfeited himſelf ſick, that he
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:55009:65"/>might have pretence to remain at <hi>Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chen.</hi> This was a cruel Neceſſity for me to leave <hi>Axione</hi> expos'd to his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities. No, ſaid I to her, when the time of my Departure was come, I will not abandon you to the Indiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretion of <hi>Hildezar;</hi> He is Maſter of all Power here, and my Misfortune hath ſwell'd his Authority. My Lord, replied ſhe, ſeeing I am near the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs, and ſeldom come out of her Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, I do not think that I have cauſe to fear any thing, and it is not his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity that diſquieteth me; it is your Life, my Lord, which will be expos'd to rebellious Arms; it is you your ſelf, it is that great Heart that burneth with a Deſire to Signalize it ſelf. Alas, my Lord, Sympathize with our Weakneſſes, do not purſue too ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently that Glory which will alwaies follow you, and in the heat of Battels forget not the Care you owe to the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of your own Life. This Mark
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:55009:66"/>of <hi>Axione</hi>'s Tenderneſs, whoſe fair Eies appear'd moiſt, touched me ſenſibly: That Life which I have Conſecrated unto you, fair <hi>Axione,</hi> replied I, will not be expos'd to ſo many Dangers as your Goodneſs perſwadeth you, but ſeeing you Ordain me, I will take Care of it, as of a Thing that you are not willing to loſe. For you, <hi>Axione,</hi> I entruſt you to your ſelf; reſiſt the Arrogancy of <hi>Hildezar,</hi> &amp; at my Return reſolve with your ſelf to put an eternal obſtacle in the way of his preſumptuous Pretenſions in giving your ſelf to a Prince that li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth only for you. Go, my Lord, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the fair Maid, whither the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour of Fate commandeth you to car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry your Arms; and if I be Miſtreſs of any of your Intereſts, aſſure your ſelf that they can never fall into more faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful hands.</p>
               <p>In this manner I took my leave of <hi>Axione,</hi> and having tenderly Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended her to my Siſter, I went out of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:55009:66"/>the Palace, accompanied with <hi>Benzid, Othrize,</hi> and ſeveral other Perſons of Quality. <hi>Hildezar,</hi> ſaid I to that Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour when he came to receive my laſt Orders, you have been deſirous to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main at <hi>Kachen;</hi> remember alwaies that I Reign there and reign juſtly, do not abuſe the Power that I have ſuffer'd you to aſſume; render unto my Siſter what you owe unto her Dignity, and above all reſpect <hi>Axione,</hi> all whoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts are mine. Excite no new Broils, whilſt I go to calm theſe that are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready ſet on foot: I dare aſſure you that I will return ſpeedily; Adieu. He anſwer'd me only with a Salutation, and I began to march, but not without anxious Apprehenſions.</p>
               <p>I may boldly ſay, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> that I ruſh'd like a Torrent upon the Rebels: They were animated by no couragi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Captain, and their Revolt being only an Effect of <hi>Hildezar</hi>'s Treachery, I had no great Trouble or Glory to van<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſh
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:55009:67"/>Men that were overcome at the firſt ſight of our Standards. My Anger permitted ſome of them to periſh for an Example to others, and how much ſoever I was inclin'd to Clemency, I could not without Reſentment conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that they were the cauſe of my Abſence from <hi>Axione.</hi> In the end, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt without the loſs of a Man, or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newing the leaſt Wound, though <hi>I</hi> did not ſpare my ſelf, <hi>I</hi> had in leſs than three Months quieted all things. The Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd ſubmitted themſelves to my Pleaſure, and <hi>I</hi> took the way to <hi>Kachen,</hi> from whence <hi>I</hi> had received many Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, none of which acquainted me with any thing that could make me ſuſpect the Miſery that waited for me. But arriving at that Town, <hi>I</hi> neither found <hi>Hildezar</hi> nor <hi>Axione.</hi> The Traytour had carried her away, and how exact ſoever <hi>Thamarize</hi> had been in obſerving her, ſhe could perceive nothing, and appear'd unto me deſperate at the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cident.
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:55009:67"/>
                  <hi>Alzine</hi> her ſelf, the innocent Daughter of ſo criminal a Father, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſted that ſhe had no hand in <hi>Hilde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi>'s Action, and couragiouſly offer'd her Blood unto me as an Atonement for the Offence <hi>I</hi> had receiv'd: <hi>I</hi> aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur'd her, as afflicted as <hi>I</hi> was, that not confounding her with the Traytor that gave her Life, <hi>I</hi> would have held her guiltleſs of all. In fine, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſtaying at <hi>Kachen, I</hi> run through all <hi>Thibet,</hi> and even expoſed my ſelf to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal Wandrings in the howling Deſarts of <hi>Xama,</hi> and after having conſum'd a great deal of time in an uſeleſs Queſt, <hi>I</hi> return'd to <hi>Kachen</hi> to ſettle Things for a longer Voyage, entruſting the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment to my Siſter, &amp; leaving her to the Conduct of <hi>Benzid</hi> and <hi>Othriz</hi> in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant Affairs, <hi>I</hi> departed from <hi>Thibet,</hi> unable to live without <hi>Axione. I</hi> ſaw almoſt all <hi>Aſia;</hi> I met with Adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, which I do not relate unto you, becauſe they have no direct Relation
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:55009:68"/>to my Love, and after a vain Search of two Years, being in <hi>Tartary,</hi> and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing through a Foreſt, that pertaineth to the King of <hi>Ergimul,</hi> I found <hi>Hildezar</hi> at the Root of a Tree, pierc'd with ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral mortal Wounds, &amp; in a condition worthy of his Treaſons: He breathed as yet, and eaſily knew me: His Miſery aſſwag'd my Anger, and I went to help him; No, my Lord ſaid he, You ought not to laviſh your Goodneſs for a Man that hath but too much abuſed it. I am Guilty, nor is it Death that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torts this Acknowledgment from me, and it's a great while ſince a juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morſe hath executed Vengeance upon me for my Treacheries. This Death is too ſweet for a Man that hath meri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the worſt of Puniſhments, ſeeing it permitteth me to ask Pardon of my Maſter. At theſe Words he would have made an Effort to raiſe himſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his Knees, but I hinder'd him, and ask'd News of <hi>Axione:</hi> He told me
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:55009:68"/>with a mournful Sigh, That he had been almoſt two Years ſeparated from her: That after he had made her wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der up and down a long time, he was aſſaulted in <hi>Tartary,</hi> by perſons that car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her away. That after that he had ſearch'd for her to no purpoſe, and that the ſame Robbers had now left him in the Condition in which I found him, becauſe he knew them, and endeavour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to make them confeſs what they had done with <hi>Axione.</hi> After that he breath'd his laſt, and having caus'd my Followers to cover his Body with a little Earth, I came ſtraight hither, where in the end, I unexpectedly found <hi>Axione.</hi> I made my ſelf known to <hi>Undkan:</hi> I have ever continued to ſee <hi>Axione;</hi> ſhe loveth me, I am cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of it; but her ſevere Vertue will not permit her to conſent to my Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs, till ſhe know her ſelf perfectly. she inform'd me, that <hi>Hildezar</hi> carried her very privily and by a ſubtle Strata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem;
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:55009:69"/>that he did not ſhew himſelf to her till long after their departure from <hi>Kachen;</hi> that he had conjur'd her to pardon his Love, that made him ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice all for her; that ſhe reproached him bitterly with his Treachery; but that nothing could make him alter his Reſolutions; and that in the end, She was violently taken from him in <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> and ſold to ſome <hi>Tartars,</hi> who gave her to the Princeſs <hi>Taxila.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philing</hi> left off ſpeaking: <hi>Almundzar</hi> admir'd his Generoſity, and <hi>Axione</hi>'s Vertue; Afterwards returning to the Intereſts of <hi>Zingis,</hi> they diſcours'd of the Troops that he had about <hi>Cambalu,</hi> and of the meaſures that were moſt proper to be taken, to avert the Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune that threaten'd the Life of that famous Prince.</p>
               <p>In the mean time, <hi>Timur</hi> the Author of all the Sufferings of ſo many Noble Perſons, was not altogether free of a reſtleſs Anxiety himſelf, and though the
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:55009:69"/>Man in the World whom he hated moſt was upon the Point of being Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crific'd unto him, having as much Love for <hi>Taxila</hi> as he was capable of, he could not live out of her Sight, and knew well that if he dar'd to preſent himſelf before her, he would doubtleſs hear nothing that would pleaſe him. <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar,</hi> who lov'd him even to Idolatry, ſaw his Melancholy with Grief: Why do ye languiſh, <hi>Timur,</hi> ſaid ſhe unto him, all Things conſpire together for your Felicity, and there is no Crown in <hi>Aſia</hi> equal to that which you ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs? What more can be done to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie you? After ſo much Care that I have taken, will you alwaies ſhew me a gloomy Countenance? Madam, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied <hi>Timur,</hi> Theſe Motions are not vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntary, and it's againſt my Will that you perceive them: You have done but too much for me: My Gratitude can never riſe high enough; but if my Ambition be contented, I feel my Love
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:55009:70"/>alarm'd. Too conſtant Lover of <hi>Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ila</hi> that <hi>I</hi> am, <hi>I</hi> muſt either deprive my ſelf of her Sight, or expoſe my ſelf to her Reproaches! Ah, Madam! How do <hi>I</hi> deſerve to be lamented? and how uneaſie do <hi>I</hi> find my ſelf in the heighth of my Proſperity! Rather ſay that you are weak, interrupted the Queen of <hi>Tartary,</hi> and that you deſerve real Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries, ſeeing you torment your ſelf with imaginary ones: Suffer our Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my firſt to periſh, and afterwards make your ſelf Maſter of <hi>Taxila.</hi> 'Tis no matter whether or no you obtain her Conſent; <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Authority will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move theſe Obſtacles. In fine, My Son, <hi>I</hi> will have you to Reign over the <hi>Tartars,</hi> and there is nothing but I will do to effectuate this Reſolution. Go ſee that ungrateful <hi>Taxila,</hi> whoſe Diſdain I bear with only upon your account, and in the mean time, I will preſs the King to put <hi>Zingis</hi> to Death.</p>
               <p>The Son of <hi>Zamar</hi> inſtigated by ſuch
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:55009:70"/>a Mother, left her and went to the Princeſs, to whom he alone had ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs. <hi>Taxila,</hi> who had not ſeen him ſince her Diſgrace, was ſo moved at the ſight of him that ſhe had almoſt loſt her Underſtanding: To follow his Mother's Advice, he had laid aſide his Sadneſs, ſo that he appear'd before her full of a bold Arrogancy. Madam, ſaid he, One would have hardly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd, that ſuch a Perſon as you had been capable to draw exil'd Enemies into <hi>Tartary,</hi> and even into the King your Father's Palace; and without reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning my Intereſt, you had others pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful enough to have diſſwaded you from ſuch a Correſpondence.</p>
               <p>As moderate as the Princeſs was, ſhe loſt all Patience at thoſe Words: Tho' I had committed ſomething that ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lig'd me to make Reparation, replied ſhe, it ſhould never be to the King of <hi>Tendur</hi> (a vile Slave of his own Vanity, and his Mother's Paſſions) that I would
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:55009:71"/>juſtifie my ſelf. This is indeed to Treat me as a Priſoner, to carry your Inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency to the place to which I am Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd: Cannot the Averſion for you that Nature hath inſpir'd me with ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie you, unleſs you augment by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings full of Injuſtice and Preſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption? Go, pretended King of <hi>Tendur,</hi> go to the Feet of the cruel <hi>Zamar,</hi> and ſollicite the Death of <hi>Zingis;</hi> but know, that into whatſoever Condition your common Fury may reduce him, he ſhall be ever dearer to me than my Life. I would never perhaps have ſaid ſo much, if he had not been miſerable; but in the preſent ſtate of our Affairs I have no Meaſures to obſerve; and all my Tenderneſs is but a mean Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence for what he hath done, and now ſuffereth for me. At theſe Words <hi>Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ila</hi> went into a Cloſet, where ſhe ſhut her ſelf up; and <hi>Timur</hi> full of Rage and Confuſion, ſaid a thouſand Things to <hi>Axione</hi> without Reſpect or Reaſon. She
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:55009:71"/>anſwer'd him with a great deal of Wit and Courage, and did not ſwerve in a Point from the Princeſs's Sentiments, which raiſed the Fury of the Son of <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi> to ſuch a heighth, that he return'd to his Mother, to bawl againſt <hi>Taxila,</hi> and haſten the Death of a Rival, whom he could not endure to ſee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd before him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Undkan</hi> ſo ardently ſollicited by per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that had all Power over him, was quickly perſwaded to a fatal Reſolution. <hi>Almundzar,</hi> whoſe Affection to <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Intereſt made him a watchful Spy over all their Actions, perceiv'd what paſt in <hi>Undkan</hi>'s Mind, and went to Advertiſe the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> of all. Then keeping no more meaſures, they diſpatch'd <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> to aſſemble the <hi>Mogols</hi> that lay near <hi>Cambalu,</hi> and <hi>Almundzar</hi> took the ſame Care for the <hi>Tartars</hi> that had declar'd in <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Favour.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Tartary</hi> deſirous to act with ſome form of Juſtice, leſt he
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:55009:72"/>ſhould draw upon himſelf the hatred of all the Earth, believ'd that it would be eſteem'd a Crime great enough to condemn the King of the <hi>Mogols,</hi> that he was ſurpriz'd in the Night-time at the Gates of his Palace, in a deſign to enter into it. <hi>Zamar</hi> made choice of the Judges, who according to her Inſtiga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions condemn'd the Illuſtrious <hi>Zingis</hi> to loſe his Head within three Days. When the Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence was pronounced, he was nothing mov'd: But the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> and <hi>Almund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> upon whom Generoſity had ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an Influence, trembling for Horrour and Anger, reſolved to loſe all or ſave <hi>Zingis.</hi> They acted with ſo much diligence and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crecy, that they quickly form'd a ſtrong Party, whom they diſpers'd through the Twelve Suburbs of the City of <hi>Cambalu,</hi> to appear in Arms, when it ſhould be time, and reſcue <hi>Zingis</hi> from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi>'s Guards. King <hi>Philing</hi> made no scruple to declare him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf Head of his Defenders: He owed no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> and did not violate any Right, in reſiſting one that endeavoured ſo barbarous an Act of Injuſtice.</p>
               <p>The Noiſe of <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Death reached the Princeſſe's Ears, who repented but too late, that ſhe had irritated the Jealouſly of <hi>Timur.</hi> She remained in the diſmal expectation of that Misfortune, ſhedding Tears in abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:55009:72"/>with her dear <hi>Axione;</hi> and that fair Maid more touch'd than ever before ſhe had been, felt a Grief not much inferiour to that of <hi>Taxila.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Day appointed for the Death of the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> being come, the Streets were crouded with a multitude of People in the Morning. He was to loſe his Life be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Palace; and it was eaſie for them that deſign'd to ſave him, to conceal them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in a Cround compoſed of all ſorts of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: The Scaffold was erected before <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar</hi>'s Apartment, that from her Chamber Windows ſhe might taſte the Pleaſure of that Spectacle. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> took his Place with <hi>Zamar, Timur,</hi> and the Kings of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ng, Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guth, Cerguth,</hi> and <hi>Ergimul,</hi> worthy Slaves of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Queen. The People beheld with Aſtoniſhment this Aſſembly of Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigns in an Occupation ſo unbecoming their Royal Dignity; whilſt the afflicted <hi>Taxila</hi> groan'd, or rather was ready to expire in the Arms of <hi>Axione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zamar</hi> who ſaw her Revenge ready to be executed, taſted the Delights that a barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Soul uſually ſindeth in cruelty: The weak <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> ſuffered himſelf to be drawn away by the ſame Motions, and the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy <hi>Timur,</hi> that declared Enemy of Vertue, prepar'd himſelf to behold the Victim that
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:55009:73"/>they were going to ſacrifice to him, as He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roes would diſpoſe themſelves to the moſt generous Exploits; that is to ſay with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Mind, and a confident Countenance; and the Four Kings bound to <hi>Zamar</hi>'s Chair, ſerv'd for an Ornament to this unworthy Triumph.</p>
               <p>Not only did the King of <hi>Thibet, Almund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar,</hi> and ſome other <hi>Tartars</hi> bolder than the reſt, murmur againſt ſo black an Attempt: Amongſt the People and Souldiers were found ſome equitable Souls, ſenſible of the Merit and Innocency of <hi>Zingis,</hi> and who on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly wanted Head to declare openly in his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour.</p>
               <p>He was brought from the Gaol about Noon, that the Sun might light the Solem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: His Guards cauſed him to mount a Chariot that waited for him, and to add Diſgrace to Cruelty, the Executioner having tyed his Hands, plac'd himſelf beſide him.</p>
               <p>The contented <hi>Zamar</hi> look'd upon all this without changing Colour: Her Courage made all thoſe that ſurrounded her tremble; and many remembring they had ſeen him in thoſe Rencounters where he had acquir'd ſo much Glory, bow'd down their Eyes, and ſigh'd mournfully, to behold ſo great a Man fall by ſo deplorable a Blow. Never had he appear'd with more Grace and Majeſty than
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:55009:73"/>in this unfortunate Condition: His Hands that had chain'd ſo many Kings, bore their Fetters without ſhrinking; he deſpiſed the Shame, and lifting up his Eyes to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens; O, <hi>Taxila!</hi> ſaid he aloud, I offer my Life to you as heartily as I would have done the Empire of the Univerſe, if it had been in my power: Receive it as a certain Proof of my faithful Affection, and remember <hi>Zingis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Chariot in the mean time advanc'd, and every where might be ſeen a Deluge of Tears: The Men excited one another to ſave <hi>Zingis,</hi> the Women begg'd his Life, and even the Children gave marks of Tenderneſs.</p>
               <p>They drew near to the great Place before the Palace, and the Croud divided themſelves at a place where the Street grew broader, to make way for the Chariot, when the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> ſtopp'd it. He would not ſuffer <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundzar</hi> to take up Arms, that he might have occaſion to act afterwards. <hi>Zerbin</hi> alone was with him, and upon the firſt Signal they gave, the <hi>Mogols</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> oppos'd the Paſſage of the Guards.</p>
               <p>This ſo unexpected an Obſtacle aſtoniſhed all the People: <hi>Zingis</hi> himſelf was ſurpriz'd with it. The firſt thing the King of <hi>Thibet</hi> did, was with one Blow of his Sword to cut off the Head of him that was to do the ſame
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:55009:74"/>Office to the King of the <hi>Mogols,</hi> and to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tye the Hands of that valiant Prince. My Lord, ſaid he, preſenting him with Arms, If you dye to Day, you ſhall not dye unaccom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied, and it ſhall be in a glorious manner. Receive this Service from a Man, who for being unknown unto you, is not the leſs in your Intereſts. <hi>Zingis</hi> took what <hi>Philing</hi> gave him, and saw himſelf quickly in a condition to carry Terrour through all: He ſtruck the <hi>Tartars</hi> therewith by his ſupernatural Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. <hi>Philing</hi> imitated him valiantly. <hi>Zerbin</hi> ſurpaſs'd himſelf. The <hi>Mogols</hi> ſeem'd to be ſo many Heroes; and the <hi>Tartars,</hi> who after what they had done could hope for no ſafety but from <hi>Zingis,</hi> did immolate their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men that favour'd <hi>Zamar</hi>'s Deſign. In ſtead of one Head that ſhould have faln that Day, Rivers of Blood cover'd the Streets of <hi>Cambalu. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> not fearing this Surprizal, had thought a part of his Guards ſufficient to ſecure <hi>Zingis,</hi> and had not arm'd the old Bands of Souldiers that remain'd in he Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs; and in a few moments <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Party cut in pieces all thoſe that reſiſted them.</p>
               <p>But with what Eye did <hi>Zamar, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> and <hi>Timur</hi> behold this Rebellion? Pride and Anger had almoſt ſtifled the Queen. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> was agitated with ſeveral Paſſions at once, and the cowardly King of <hi>Tendur</hi> grew pale
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:55009:74"/>for fear, not doubting but that he would be oblig'd to expoſe himſelf to <hi>Zingis</hi>'s Valour, which he had ſo often experimented. <hi>Zamar</hi> to no purpoſe excited the <hi>Tartars</hi> with Cries and Promiſes, the feebler ſort fled, and the braveſt durſt not advance. The Kings them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves whoſe Submiſſions made her ſo haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, ſtood unmoveable without attempting any thing. What, ſaid ſhe, beholding them at her Palace-Gate, in the preſence of five other Kings, ſhall a daring Criminal triumph over the Laws and our Authority, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps load us with the Iron that he is freed from? O mad Fortune! how great is thy Fury and blindneſs this Day? Theſe Words covered thoſe that heard them with confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion: but ſhe had not the power to inſpire them with Courage. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> whoſe Safety was intereſted in this Affair, as well as his Glory; and who notwithſtanding the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of his Years, was perhaps the braveſt of all theſe Kings, went out, and the reſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed him: they ſent Orders to the Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers to advance, and led on thoſe that were able to bear Arms in the Palace. As <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Philing</hi> were at the point of making themſelves Maſters of the Place, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> rally'd thoſe that ſled; but his Blood was quickly frozen when he beheld the Prodigies that theſe two Kings per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd.
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:55009:75"/>
                  <hi>Zingis</hi> knew him, and might have eaſily turn'd againſt him that admirable Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that had before done him ſo great Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices; but reſpecting him who had given life to the Princeſs, he turn'd his Sword elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where, when he ſaw a Knight that had joyn'd his Party ſome moments before, lift up his Arm to kill <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan.</hi> The generous <hi>Zingis</hi> not contenting himſelf to have ſpar'd his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuter, would yet defend him againſt his own Friends, and oppoſing himſelf to the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liant Man that fought on his ſide; Stop, who ever thou art, ſaid he to him, and do not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>file thy Arms with the Blood of <hi>Taxila</hi>'s Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> was no more ſurpriz'd at this Action than was the Unknown, to whom Examples of Vertue were familiar. All the World remark'd the proceeding of <hi>Zingis,</hi> and <hi>Philing</hi> was ſo charm'd with it, that his Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection for ſo great a Man augmented. The King of <hi>Tartary</hi> retir'd amongſt his Men pale and trembling, and in the mean time the old Band of Souldiers, who were Quarter'd in the Suburds, as we told you before, and who had time to make themſelves ready, came pouring in on all ſides. Aſſoon as the cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ardly <hi>Timur</hi> ſaw them appear, he ſhouted for joy, and advanc'd at their Head; but how dear did his boldneſs coſt him! <hi>Zingis</hi> who had appear'd ſo moderate in reſpect of the
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:55009:75"/>Princeſſe's Father was not ſo in reſpect of an inſolent Rival; but violently leaping up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him; Thou ſhalt dye, without poſſeſſing <hi>Taxila,</hi> ſaid he, and thy Eyes ſhall not be Witneſſes of the death of <hi>Zingis.</hi> A Shower of Blows followed theſe Words, and the Son of <hi>Zamar</hi> fell down lifeleſs at the Feet of the King of the <hi>Mogols:</hi> His Fall overwhelm'd the Heart of his Mother, who encouraged him from the Windows, with all that Grief and Rage hath moſt violent. She blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Heaven and Men, and even revil'd her Husband, falling into Convulſions, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>token'd the cruelty of her Paſſions.</p>
               <p>Whilſt <hi>Zingis, Philing, Zerbin,</hi> the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>known, and the <hi>Mogols,</hi> with a part of the <hi>Tartars,</hi> compleated the Victory: <hi>Almund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> ſeeing the Princeſſe's Apartment without Guards, run thither and found her frighted at the noiſe which ſhe heard, without know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Cauſe thereof. Ah, <hi>Almundzar,</hi> ſaid ſhe to him! Is the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> dead? No, Madam, anſwered the <hi>Tartar,</hi> and I hope you ſhall ſee him ſhortly in a Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to put an end to all your Alarm? Then he related to her all that had paſt; and ſeeing ſhe was no Lover of Blood, the Death of <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur</hi> did not pleaſe her, how great ſoever the Advantage was that ſhe receiv'd by it. But of all that which touch'd her in Favour of
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:55009:76"/>
                  <hi>Zingis,</hi> nothing had ſo great an Influence up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on her as the glorious Action, which had af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forded the <hi>Tartars</hi> ſo great a cauſe of Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. O Heaven! ſaid ſhe, If <hi>Zingis</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted and ready to ſuccumb under the pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tileſs Sword of his Enemies, defendeth the Father of <hi>Taxila</hi> againſt thoſe whom Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roſity arm'd to ſave him from the Fury of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> what doth not ſhe owe to ſo ſtrong Marks of ſo pure a Love? <hi>Axione</hi> being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſted for her Lover, and for a Prince whom ſhe tenderly lov'd, reaſſumed Hope with the Princeſs; and they redoubled their Vows.</p>
               <p>Fortune had entirely declar'd againſt <hi>Za<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mar:</hi> The loſs of her dear <hi>Timur</hi> was follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Death of ſeveral thouſands of Souldiers. The King of <hi>Cerguth, Tenguth, Ergimul</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ng</hi> fighting faintly with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Valour and Courage, periſh'd by the Arms of <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Philing,</hi> and the <hi>Tartars</hi> that came from the Suburbs, were conſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to give back.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Zingis</hi> had no deſign upon <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi>'s Crown. Seeing that Prince ſtunn'd with the Diſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der re-enter his Palace, he embrac'd the King of <hi>Thibet,</hi> with whom the affectionate <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bin</hi> made him acquainted, and after having ſaid unto him all that a juſt Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment can dictate to a generous Heart, he
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:55009:76"/>turn'd toward the valiant Man that had fought with ſo much advantage, and ſeeing his Head diſcover'd, he knew him to be the Prince of <hi>Brema:</hi> Then it was that their mutual Embraces expreſs'd their Friendſhip. <hi>Zingis</hi> prais'd the <hi>Mogols</hi> and <hi>Tartars</hi> that had ſerv'd him, with all the affection that their Valour oblig'd him to. His Friends adviſed him to go into the Palace; but whatſoever Impatience he had to ſee <hi>Taxila,</hi> he judg'd that out of reſpect to her he ought not to leave <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> and retir'd to the ſame Houſe where he had lain ſometime abſconded. <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> and <hi>Omir</hi> accompanied him thither, and <hi>Zerbin</hi> took care of the remainder of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gols.</hi> But ſcarce had they been two Hours in that place, when <hi>Almundzar</hi> came to ſeek them. Come, valiant Princes, ſaid he to them, with immoderate tranſports of Joy, come and enjoy the Fruits of your Valour; you have no more enemies to fear: Fury hath exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted upon <hi>Zamar,</hi> what your Arms have done upon the reſt; She is dead, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> freed from the Bondage in which her Artifices had enthral'd him, recalleth that Vertue which ſhe had baniſhed out of his Soul, and with ardent Breathings deſireth a Reconciliation with you. Theſe Words which inſpir'd them with Hopes of an agreeable Revolution, did not at firſt find a perfect belief in thoſe to
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:55009:77"/>whom they were addreſs'd; but in the end, they were oblig'd to give Faith unto them, and follow <hi>Almundzar</hi> to the Palace. Peace was already re-eſtabliſhed there; all the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple made Vows for <hi>Zingis;</hi> there were none found lamenting for <hi>Zamar,</hi> and much leſs for her wicked Son.</p>
               <p>Coming to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan, Zingis</hi> found there the Princeſs, and <hi>Philing</hi> the charming <hi>Axione:</hi> The King of <hi>Tartary</hi> with open Arms recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the King of the <hi>Mogols,</hi> and that Prince humbled himſelf reſpectfully to receive his Embraces. Will you forget the Cruelties that cover me with an eternal Shame? My Lord, ſaid he to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> and can you pardon me for what the unjuſt Empire, that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man had uſurp'd over my Weakneſs, hath made me commit againſt you, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many Services that you had ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly render'd unto me? By your firſt Acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons you merited the Crown to <hi>Tartary,</hi> and all that you have added unto it; and by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving my Life for the ſake of <hi>Taxila,</hi> you deſerve alſo that Princeſs: I give her unto you, <hi>Zingis,</hi> and with her <hi>Tartary,</hi> and all that is ſubjected to my Scepter, being ſenſible of no other Pleaſure than in ſeeing you two Reign together. At theſe words he took the Princeſs by the Hand, who full of Joy receiv'd that of <hi>Zingis.</hi> My Lord, ſaid he to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi>
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:55009:77"/>Your Goodneſs ſurpaſſeth infinitely my Hopes and the Merit of my Services. I receive with all due reſpect the precious Advantage of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united to the Princeſs: but for the Crown of <hi>Tartary,</hi> I will not joyn mine to it, but to the end that I may make you Maſter of both. Reign my Lord, Reign in Peace, and receive my Homages. No, no, interrupted <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> I have been King too long, ſince I have been guilty of ſo great Injuſtice in that quality: whilſt I Reign in you, you ſhall Reign for me, and I will reap from thence both Pleaſure and Glory. Then he asked Pardon of the King of <hi>Thibet,</hi> prais'd his Generoſity, and was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly reconcil'd to him. But caſting his Eyes upon the Prince of <hi>Brema,</hi> who had not yet chang'd his Habits, he knew him to be that terrible Man againſt whom <hi>Zingis</hi> had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended him. He was ſomewhat mov'd at the ſight of him; but the riſing Vertue, which begun to chaſe from his Soul all that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach'd to Vice, would not permit him to entertain any Reſentment. He embrac'd him then as he would have done a Son: The King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> would not ſuffer you to take Vengeance on me, <hi>Omir,</hi> ſaid he unto him, and I will not find fault with one that attack'd me in ſo juſt a Cauſe. <hi>Omir</hi> anſwer'd with a great deal of ſubmiſſion. <hi>Almundzar</hi> received alſo new Marks of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi>'s Friendſhip, and
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:55009:78"/>this King ſpoke with much ſweetneſs to all thoſe that took Arms for <hi>Zingis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Mean-time Love triumph'd, and <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Taxila</hi> perceiv'd it mutually in their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented Eyes, and received from one another the moſt tender Aſſurances thereof. <hi>Philing</hi> told <hi>Axione</hi> all that he had ſuffered during a few Days abſence, and conjur'd that ſcrupu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous perſon to be ſomewhat leſs fix'd in her Reſolutions, and to yield at laſt to make them happy. She thanked him for what he had done for <hi>Zingis;</hi> and after this firſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terview, the Princes having received ſome ſlight Wounds that had need to be look'd af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; went out together with <hi>Almundzar:</hi> They were not conſiderable enough to oblige them to keep their Chamber, and they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>par'd themſelves to viſit the Princeſs, when the Prince of <hi>Brema</hi> ſpoke in this manner to the King of <hi>Thibet:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I know not, my Lord, whether what hath happen'd unto me in your Dominions will draw upon me your hatred: I have commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a Fault, and yet cannot be a Penitent. The Princeſs <hi>Thamarize</hi> is at <hi>Cambalu;</hi> it is I who brought her hither; but when you ſhall hear my Reaſons, you will perhaps par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me.</p>
               <p>This Diſcourſe aſtoniſh'd <hi>Philing:</hi> He did not doubt but Love had been the principal
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:55009:78"/>Agent in the Affair; and ſeeing he had not a Heart diſpos'd to condemn that Paſſion, that had ſo great an Empire over him, ſeeing the Prince of <hi>Brema</hi>'s Worth, and knowing the Service that he had done to <hi>Axione.</hi> What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever you have done, my Lord, replyed he, I am perſwaded that my Siſter is oblig'd to you, and I being ſo, in ſo touching a manner, believe that I am incapable to condemn you: But ſince <hi>Thamarize</hi> is at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> let us ſee her quickly, that ſhe may receive the Embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of a Brother that hath always dearly lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Philing</hi> and <hi>Zingis</hi> would have accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied <hi>Omir;</hi> but <hi>Almundzar</hi> pray'd them not to ſtir, and he went with that Prince to ſeek <hi>Thamarize,</hi> whom they immediately brought to <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi>'s Palace: The Brother and the Siſter gave to one another all the marks of a tender Friendſhip. <hi>Zingis</hi> ſaluted the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs of <hi>Thibet,</hi> whoſe Beauty he admir'd, and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> hearing of her Arrival, came to ſee her, that he might ſhew the greatneſs of his Reſpect for <hi>Timur,</hi> and would himſelf lead her into an Apartment whither <hi>Taxila</hi> and <hi>Axione</hi> alſo came. As ſoon as <hi>Thamarize</hi> had ſaluted the Princeſs of <hi>Tartary,</hi> ſhe received <hi>Axione</hi> with open Arms; and ſhe received her Careſſes with a reſpectful tenderneſs. The King retir'd, and all the Company being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſirous
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:55009:79"/>to be inform'd how <hi>Omir</hi> and <hi>Thama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize</hi> were come together, the Prince of <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> with the Princeſſe's permiſſion, ſpoke in this manner to theſe Illuſtrious Perſons.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Hiſtory of <hi>OMIR</hi> and <hi>THAMIRIZE.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere are none but know that I have been unhappy from the Cradle; the Son of a Prince Conquer'd and Subdu'd by the King of <hi>Tartary</hi>'s Arms, without For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, having loſt all in that Revolution; and without hope to re-eſtabliſh my Houſe, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs by my own Courage, and the aſſiſtance of my Friends.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> did not neglect my Education; and I muſt own my ſelf oblig'd to him, in that I was brought up as the Son of a King: but having attain'd to a more reaſonable Age, <hi>Timur</hi>'s Inſolency made me perceive that I was only a Slave, he always treating me as his Inferiour. I bore all a great while, not knowing what to reſolve upon. The Arrival of <hi>Zingis</hi> into <hi>Tartary</hi> ſtay'd me there, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Affection that I bore to him: we made our firſt Campaign together; but at our return from the War, not being able to live under a Power which <hi>Zamar</hi>'s Authority
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:55009:79"/>and <hi>Timur</hi>'s Credit render'd unjuſt, I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from <hi>Tartary</hi> without acquainting any with my Reſolution, and firſt viſited the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate Place where I firſt ſaw light: Such ſad Objects ſerv'd only to afflict me; I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended towards the South, and inſenſibly came into the Kingdom of <hi>Thibet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I arriv'd at <hi>Kachen</hi> a little after the King had left it: Sadneſs reigned over all; thoſe that govern'd the State taking advantage of the King's Abſence, and of the ſmall Experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence that the Princeſs had in theſe great Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, minded their own Profit, and uſurp'd too great an Authority.</p>
               <p>The firſt time I ſaw <hi>Thamirize</hi> was in the Temple, where ſhe was performing her De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions: Her modeſt and melancholy Air render'd her Beauty All-potent over my Heart: I perceiv'd even then that I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning to fall in love, and I had not the force to reſiſt this Diſpoſition. Having ſeen her a moment, I burn'd with a deſire to ſee her again: but how could I have Acceſs to her? <hi>Philing</hi>'s Abſence made the Court ſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary, and the Palace inacceſſible to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers. I was conſtrain'd then to expect from Fortune the Occaſions of ſatisfying my ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Paſſion. The Idea of <hi>Thamirize</hi> never forſook me; I return'd into the Temple, but becauſe it was publick, ſhe came thither but ſeldom.</p>
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:55009:80"/>
               <p>I learn'd, after a ſmall abode at <hi>Kachen,</hi> that ſince the King's departure, the Princeſs liv'd retired: that Men had no acceſs to her, not thoſe even of the greateſt Quality, that ſhe ſpent her time in Reading, Walking, or ſome other Occupations of that nature. They whom I came acquainted with made a Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traicture of her Humour, and charm'd me; they told me that ſhe was Generous, Pitiful, of an eaſie Acceſs to thoſe that had Buſineſs with her, witty in Converſation, and inca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of doing an Injuſtice: She had ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Maids of Illuſtrious Families about her, and this little Court, ſo ſevere to our Sex, inſpir'd my youthful Fancy with a deſign as odd as bold, but the only one that gave me Hopes of Succeſs: being of convenient Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I reſolved to cloath my ſelf like a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. They wear their Habits ſomewhat looſe in <hi>Thibet,</hi> I caus'd ſome to be made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for a Perſon of Quality, by means of a Girl whom I acquir'd, and who was faithful unto me. There was none but would have been deceiv'd with this Diſguiſe, even thoſe of my moſt familiar Acquaintance, there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing nothing forc'd in my Actions, and my Face might have paſt for that of a handſome Maid.</p>
               <p>Over-joy'd that I had faln upon this Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagem, I reſolved quickly to make an Eſſay,
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:55009:80"/>and in two Days having perfectly accuſtom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed my ſelf to act the Maid, I was ſhewed the way to the Palace-Garden, into which my Cloths eaſily obtain'd for me a permiſſion to enter. I walked there a great while alone; but at laſt <hi>Thamirize</hi> who was wont to come thither daily, came at her uſual Hour, and paſt by near the place where I was: I ſaluted her reſpectfully; ſhe return'd my Salutation with an extraordinary Goodneſs; and after ſhe had walked ſome paces off, the Idea of my unknown Face ſtriking her Imagination, ſhe asked of the Maids that followed her, whether any of them knew me: They all an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in the Negative, and it being the will of Fortune, that the Princeſs ſhould find ſomething in me not unworthy of her Curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oſity, ſhe ſat down, and order'd one of her Maids to entreat me to come to her: I o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed with a great Agitation, and <hi>Thamirize</hi> took it for a ſign of Modeſty, that which was only the Effect of my Love. Do not take it ill, ſaid ſhe unto me, with a graceful Sweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, that I am deſirous to know you: Your Meen is able to pre-occupy all thoſe that ſee you, in your Favour; I wiſh I could be uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to you to teſtifie that I ſpeak ſincerely to you.</p>
               <p>Theſe obliging Words pierc'd to the very bottom of my Heart, and filled it with a very
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:55009:81"/>ſenſible Joy. I was indeed inform'd, Madam, replied I, that you was a Princeſs as Generous as Fair; and that the Misfortunes of my Love would certainly be remedied by your Goodneſs, if I could once appear before you: I was Born in <hi>Tartary,</hi> Madam, and Educa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> with the Princeſs <hi>Taxila,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a Quality that procur'd me that Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour. Certain deplorable Misfortunes oblig'd me to leave that Court, and Heaven con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted me to <hi>Thibet,</hi> where I abide, that I may evite greater Evils; unknown to all your People, without Protection, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Friends, I have already paſt ſome ſad Days here: but, Madam, they will be hereafter more pleaſant, and the Happineſs that I have this Day received, will make me forget all my paſt Pains. <hi>Thamirize</hi> looked upon me attentively all the while, I ſpoke, and offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her hand to me with an Air full of Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; I am ſorry, ſaid ſhe to me, that For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune hath been ſo ungrateful to your Merit, as to expoſe you to any croſs Adventures: but at the ſame time, I am glad that ſhe affordeth me an Occaſion to aſſiſt you. You may abide with us, and nothing that dependeth on us ſhall be wanting to make your Life eaſie.</p>
               <p>I caſt my ſelf at the Princeſſe's Feet, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported with Love and delight; and having thanked her for the Favour ſhe did me, I en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain'd
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:55009:81"/>her with a recital of my Adventure, as my Fancy at that inſtant dictated to me, ſtill keeping within the bounds of probabili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and told her that my Name was <hi>Irmiſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was the ſucceſs of my Stratagem of Love: I abode in the Palace among <hi>Thamiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ze</hi>'s Maids, and forgot no Precautions that might ſerve to conceal my Secret, and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue me in a quiet poſſeſſion of the Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage that I enjoyed. In a little time I acquir'd a conſiderable rank in the Princeſſe's Friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; ſhe gave me a thouſand innocent marks thereof, and ſeem'd delighted to hear me talk: but my greateſt trouble was to hide my Love, which received new augmentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons every moment: I had this advantage in my Happineſs, that it did not excite any Envy againſt me, and that all <hi>Thamirize</hi>'s Maids were my Friends. <hi>Alzine</hi> the Daughter of one <hi>Hildezar</hi> a Fugitive, and the cauſe of the King's Abſence, did often bewail her Father's Crime before the Princeſs, who inform'd me that it was <hi>Axione</hi> who had obliged their Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to leave his Kingdom, and ſhe was not a little joy'd, when I told her news of that lovely <hi>Axione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>My greateſt care was not to abuſe the Princeſſe's Goodneſs, by allowing too great a liberty to my Eyes: I ſhunn'd her Preſence at thoſe Hours that Decency forbids us to ſee
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:55009:82"/>Women in; I never went to her Chamber till ſhe was dreſs'd, and came out of it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways before they put her to Bed.</p>
               <p>In this manner then I paſt my time the firſt Month; but I could not expect to remain ſtill without trouble. The abſence of the King and <hi>Hildezar,</hi> who was the moſt conſiderable after that Prince, ſwell'd the Courage of ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral perſons, that dared not to pretend to any thing before. For believing that neither of them would ever return, and ſeeing the Princeſs deſtin'd to Reign after <hi>Philing, O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrize</hi> and <hi>Benzide,</hi> who were of the quality of Princes, appeared in love with her, and declar'd it openly. The King had judged them capable to give advice to <hi>Thamirize,</hi> the youngeſt of them being above 30 Years of Age at his departure from <hi>Thibet,</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended unto them the State, and a Siſter whom he dearly loved, and they made a ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical uſe of this Recommendation.</p>
               <p>Though <hi>Thamirize</hi> was deſirous to ſhun all Men, theſe two had Priviledges that ſhe could not oppoſe: As ſoon as they knew one another to be Rivals, Jealouſie ſet them at odds; they had both Pride and very little Merit; and a Soul ſo delicate as that of the Princeſs could not be touch'd in their Favour. For me, I ſoon perceiv'd that their Love was intereſted and void of reſpect. They had
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:55009:82"/>heard of my Adventures, and ſeeing the Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit that I had with <hi>Thamirize,</hi> both of them endeavour'd to gain me to their ſide, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treated me to promote the Intereſt of their Loves. As they both made the ſame Harangues unto me, I return'd to both a like Anſwer. My Lord, ſaid I to <hi>Benzide,</hi> who was oldeſt, and as I believ'd, wiſeſt, the Princeſs is too judicious her ſelf to ask Advice of me con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning your Propoſals: but though ſhe ſhould do it, and addreſs her ſelf to me, I would ſend her back to conſult her own Heart and Reaſon, which are alone capable to regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Sentiments of ſuch a Perſon as ſhe: But ſeeing you honour me with your Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, permit me to tell you, that of the hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour I take her to be, declared Lovers will meet with no good Reception from her, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in the King's abſence. <hi>Philing</hi> replied, <hi>Benzide</hi> will never return to <hi>Kachen,</hi> and the cauſe that carried him hence will doubtleſs prove his ruine: It is not that which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexeth me, and all the cauſe of my diſquiet, is, that I am ignorant of the difference that <hi>Thamirize</hi> putteth between <hi>Othrize</hi> and me. I believe, ſaid I, that ſhe putteth none at all. Well then, continued <hi>Benzide,</hi> not well ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with me, I muſt make a difference, and I hope ſhall be able enough to do it. He left me, and the Princeſs perceiving that he went
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:55009:83"/>away vox'd, approach'd to reſcue me out of a thoughtfulneſs into which this Diſcourſe had put me. Are you my Rival, <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> ſaid ſhe to me ſmiling, and hath <hi>Benzide</hi> been making a Love-declaration to you? Ah! how would I be obliged to your Beauty, if it had freed me from his Importunities: I am only <hi>Benzide</hi>'s Confident, Madam, anſwered I; He ſolicites me to promote his Intereſt with you, and wiſheth that I could render him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable unto you. My dear <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> replied ſhe ſighing, I fear <hi>Benzide</hi> and <hi>Othriz</hi> will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex me ſadly. Nor was this Fear groundleſs, and never two ambitious Men puſh'd their Timerity to a greater height.</p>
               <p>For me, I liv'd with more equitable but no leſs diſquieting Deſires: The Beauties of <hi>Thamirize</hi> flatter'd the preſent time, but they gave me no Hopes for the future. I was guilty of deceiving her by a criminal Artifice; and however pure my Intentions were, I had cauſe to believe that ſhe would not leave my Fallacy unpuniſhed. After I had ſatisfied blindly the firſt motions of my Love, theſe Reflections rack'd my Soul; the leaſt look of the Princeſs alarm'd me; I ſtill fancied that ſhe read the Truth in my Heart, and that ſhe had diſcover'd my Sex. This plung'd me into ſo profound a Melancholy, that I was often in a doubt whether I ſhould declare my Crime,
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:55009:83"/>and expoſe my ſelf to her juſt Indignation, and receive the Puniſhment that I merited, or baniſh my ſelf from her, and preſerve my Crime eternally ſecret. Theſe Agitations made a great impreſſion both on my Body and Mind. <hi>Thamirize</hi> who lov'd me, percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this alteration with Grief. <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> ſaid ſhe to me, one Evening, when I was alone with her, I am thinking on you, though I believe you do not think on me. It is doubtleſs the ill Fortune that brought you into <hi>Thibet,</hi> that inſpireth you with that Melancholy, which I cannot ſee without trouble, and which I wiſh I was able to remove at any rate. Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, replied I, Since you have ſweetned, or rather fix'd that cruel Fortune, which croſt my tenderer Years, it is impoſſible that I can be one moment without thinking on my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations to you. Alas, Madam! I am far from being guilty of the Crime of not think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon you, and if you had never another to reproach me with, I would perhaps be leſs diſquieted. I bluſh'd in pronouncing theſe words. <hi>Thamirize</hi> perceiv'd it, and look'd upon me fixedly; but not comprehending any thing of the myſtery: I do not believe, replied ſhe, that any thing can make you paſs for guilty in my eſteem: But, <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> ſpeak ſincerely, and if you deſire my ſatisfaction, tell me why you languiſh? If there appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth any Fire in your Eyes, you look as if you
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:55009:84"/>deſign'd to hide it. I never ſurprize you but ſighing; you ſometimes look up to Heaven in a ſuppliant manner; you ſeem'd diligent in ſerving me at the beginning of our ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance, and now methinks my Preſence troubleth you. You are free here, and I did not give you a Sanctuary with a deſign to conſtrain you: But, my dear <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> added ſhe ſmiling, and ſtretching out her hand ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligingly to me, you muſt diſcover your Mind to me. I believe you are in love, and that ſome Illuſtrious <hi>Tartar</hi> poſſeſſeth that Heart, in which I am deſirous to have a little room. During this Diſcourſe I was a hundred times tempted to declare my ſelf, but conſidering that <hi>Thamirize</hi> would then perhaps ſhew me as much Severity, as ſhe had hitherto done Sweetneſs, I impriſon'd my Love once more, and endeavour'd to compoſe my ſelf.</p>
               <p>If any one had a larger ſhare in my Heart than the Princeſs of <hi>Thibet,</hi> anſwer'd I, I would never perhaps have ſeen her, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the humour I am of, I could hardly leave the place where I was ſtaid by ſo ſtrong a tye. I do not ſay, continu'd I, that my Soul is altogether void of Tenderneſs, and that is perhaps the cauſe of my languiſhing Groans. I don't doubt, ſaid <hi>Thamariſe,</hi> more perplex'd than before, but you are capable to make a good choice, and upon this account, I promiſe to be always favourable to him that hath the
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:55009:84"/>Happineſs to pleaſe you. And what would you ſay, Madam, replied I, You that have ſo much Reaſon and Wiſdom, if you found a Girl reſolute enough to love, and ſo bold as to own it. I would not condemn her for a Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom that I had forc'd her unto, anſwered <hi>Thamirize;</hi> and ſeeing there may be a lawful Tenderneſs, I would not eſteem her the leſs. Since you approve in me, replied I, a Paſſion which ſo many condemn; one would be tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pted to think that a Prince worthy of you by his Merit and Perſon, might one Day have the Honour to touch you. 'Tis true, continu'd <hi>Thamirize</hi> with a modeſt Bluſh, that I do not feel my ſelf incapable of loving an extream lovely Object; and you ſee, <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing I love you, that I am not inſenſible. Ah, Madam! cried I out, The Love with which you honour me, would not ſatisfie an amorous Prince; and I know ſome that would not be contented with it, as precious as it is. Seeing you have travell'd through Paths that are as yet unknown to me, added the Princeſs, you are able to give me a Leſſon: But, <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> ſince it is not in favour of <hi>Benzid</hi> and <hi>Othrize,</hi> that I deſign to make uſe of your Skill, we muſt expect ſome other occaſion.</p>
               <p>I was not ſorry that I had found a pretext to cover my Melancholy: I ſuffer'd <hi>Thami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rize</hi> to believe that I was in love, and after this diſcourſe ſhe ask'd me no more queſtions.</p>
               <pb n="164" facs="tcp:55009:85"/>
               <p>About this time the two Rivals redoubled their Importunities, and began to form Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties under-hand in <hi>Thibet:</hi> On this Occaſion it was that I admir'd the inconſtancy of the People. Thus <hi>Philing</hi> had only left <hi>Kachen</hi> for a Voyage, his ungrateful Subjects no ſooner ſaw he was gone, but they flatter'd the Ambition of the two Uſurpers, declaring that they would not live without a King, and that the Princeſs to Reign alone, the hope of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward embolden'd intereſted Souls, and <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirize</hi>'s Lovers had but too many Abettors.</p>
               <p>They had managed their Plots ſo cloſely, that we could not foreſee what happen'd: Theſe two Men inſpir'd by the ſame Intereſt, acted in the ſame manner; and one Morning when the Princeſs was in the Garden with her ordinary Train, that is to ſay, ſome of her Guard and her Maids, we ſaw <hi>Benzide</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proaching at the Head of many armed Men, with as proud an Air as if he had been march<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on ſome glorious Expedition; and <hi>Othrize</hi> appear'd on the other ſide with an equal num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Perſons, and a like Arrogancy. Ah, <hi>Ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe!</hi> ſaid the Princeſs unto me, What is the cauſe of the coming of theſe Princes to Day, and what do they ſeek for with ſo many ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Men and Souldiers? I had already gueſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed at their Deſign; I did not doubt but that they intended to make themſelves Maſters of <hi>Thamirize</hi>'s Liberty, and being reſolved to
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:55009:85"/>periſh for her ſake; be not frighted, Madam, replied I, Heaven doth not protect Violence, and you are not ſo far abandon'd to their Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, as you perhaps fear. As I finiſhed theſe Words, they both drew near to the Princeſs: but it was not to her that they ſpoke. What come you to ſeek for here, ſaid <hi>Benzide</hi> to <hi>Othrize?</hi> And what Buſineſs do you pretend here, replied the laſt? I perceive that both our Deſigns are the ſame: Let us fight for <hi>Thamarize,</hi> ſince it is by Arms that we muſt decide our quarrel. Then did they begin to let fly at one another, with more fury than skill; and as long as they exerciſed their Valour in this manner, I remain'd an uſeleſs Spectator of their Combat. But <hi>Othrize</hi> more happy than <hi>Benzide,</hi> laid him along at his Feet dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly wounded, and putting his Enemies to the rout, run to ſeize upon the Princeſs. Then it was that I begun to feel what I was, and no conſideration could retain me. Will you ſuffer your Princeſs to be captivated, ſaid I to the Guards, and will you not rather dye, than ſhew your ſelves ſo baſe and treacherous? <hi>Othrize</hi>'s Party was ſtrong, for he had loſt few Men, and <hi>Thamarize</hi> had but a ſmall number of her Guards with her: but not contenting my ſelf with animating them by Words, but deſirous to give them an Example, I laid hold on a Dead-man's Sword, and notwithſtanding that my Habit cumber'd me, I fought with
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:55009:86"/>an ardour that aſtoniſh'd the Princeſs. He that had often fought for indifferent Intereſts with ſome Advantage, could not be ſlow in defeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Thamirize</hi>'s Enemies, who full of Fear, and ſurrounded with her Maids, look'd upon that which ſhe eſteem'd a Prodigy. The Guards believ'd that it was an Aid miracu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly ſent from Heaven, and beſtirr'd them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with the greater Bravery: I ſhed a great deal of Blood; this could not be done without loſing ſome of my own, and coming up cloſe to <hi>Othrize,</hi> I wounded him in ſeveral places; but as he fell pierc'd with my ſtrokes, his Party yielding to the Valour of the Guards, one that was full of Affection to <hi>Othrize</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing mortally wounded and mad to find him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the Agony of Death, came behind me and thruſt his Sword quite through my Body. This grievous Blow ſent me to the Ground alſo, and the Earth that receiv'd my Body, made the Sword that ſtuck in it fall out.</p>
               <p>The Princeſs ſaw her ſelf without a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tector and Enemies both at once; Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionating my Misfortune, and believing my Death contain, ſhe run through dead and dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Men, and finding me in a condition wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of her Tears, ſhe ſhed them in abundance. <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> ſaid ſhe unto me, my dear <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> Why did you precipitate your ſelf into Danger? If my Repoſe be purchas'd at the rate of your Life, I ſhall never enjoy it with Delight. I
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:55009:86"/>am not worthy of Life, anſwer'd I, with a feeble Voice, and the Blood that I give to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tone for my Crime, is not ſufficient to waſh it away. Withdraw, Madam, think on your own Safety, and leave the unhappy <hi>Omir</hi> Prince of <hi>Brema,</hi> who that abus'd your Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, but dyeth adoring you, and who never would have done you any Offence, if he had not lov'd you too ardently. I could not ſpeak any longer; <hi>Thamirize</hi> believed I was dead, and, as ſhe ſince told me, was more ſenſible of Grief than Anger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Benzide</hi> &amp; <hi>Othrize</hi> were dangerouſly woun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dep, but not kill'd: Their Creatures took care of them, and by the Princeſſe's order I was carried into an Apartment of the Palace: E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one was aſtoniſh'd, when they were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of my Sex; but of all thoſe that were in the Princeſſe's Intereſts, not one endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour'd to incenſe her againſt me.</p>
               <p>She complain'd highly of the Violence of the two Princes; but ſeeing they had pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>occupied the Spirits of the People, and ere long were out of all danger, and in a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to begin their Perſecutions afreſh; Her Words were in vain, and ſhe ſaw that the baſeneſs of the people would abandon her to their Ambition. My Cure went on more ſlowly, becauſe I ſuffer'd more: They doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed even at firſt whether I could eſcape. In the mean time my reſtleſs Anxiety was very cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el:
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:55009:87"/>I did not ſee the Princeſs, and I could not perſwade my ſelf, that ſhe had any more In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in me, but I was very carefully tended in the mean time.</p>
               <p>When I was altogether out of danger, and in a condition to entertain a Diſcourſe, <hi>Tha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mirize</hi> came one Evening to the Chamber where I lay with her Maids: I did not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect her, and I never was ſo much mov'd. When I had ſaluted her as reſpectfully as the preſent poſture I was in could permit me, ſhe ſate down, and after ſome moments of ſilence; You have deceived me, my Lord, ſaid ſhe, and a more furious perſon than I would doubtleſs have made a noiſe if they had recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſuch an Offence: but you have ſerved me, and I am willing to forget ſo great an Injury in conſideration of ſo conſiderable a Service. Theſe are my Sentiments, my Lord; but how can I juſtifie my ſelf to the Publick? Who can believe that you have liv'd diſguis'd in the Palace without my knowledge? And what will the King my Brother think of ſuch an Adventure, when he ſhall be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd of it? Ah, my Lord! How much Vexation would you have ſpared me, if you had been more circumſpect.</p>
               <p>All that the Princeſs ſaid was ſo full of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, that it could not but inſpire me with a true Remorſe: She ſaw in my Confuſion that I was a ſuppliant Criminal; I dare ſay
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:55009:87"/>nothing in my own juſtification, Madam, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer'd I when ſhe had left off ſpeaking; I am guilty, and will ſuffer without Complaint all the Puniſhments to which your juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment may condemn me. They that are acquainted with the Power of Love, will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps have ſome Indulgence for me, but I can expect none from you, and I muſt dye for your Satisfaction. What cauſe ſoever of Vex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation you have given me, interrupted <hi>Thami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe,</hi> I demand no ſuch Reparation. Live, my Lord, and think only on your Departure from <hi>Thibet,</hi> where I can ſuffer you no longer with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſhame. And you are not revengeful, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrupted I next, in chooſing for me a Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſo great as that of Abſence. If you will condemn me to it, I muſt obey, but it will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly kill me; ſince that I might ſee you, I adventur'd even to offend you, it is beyond all doubt that my Life is bound up in that Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. After all, Madam, I will notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing be gone, and at this very moment, if my Strength would permit me. No, no, my Lord, replied the Princeſs, with a leſs imperious Air, recover your Health firſt, and when that is done, we ſhall determine the time of that Departure that diſquieteth you. She left me after theſe Words, and paſs'd the Night pretty calmly.</p>
               <p>The Sight of the Princeſs had ſuch an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence upon me, that in a little time I left my
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:55009:88"/>Bed, and then my Chamber: but in another Figure than that of a Maid, notwithſtanding the Fury and Jealouſy of <hi>Benzide</hi> and <hi>Othrize.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I went to ſee the Princeſs trembling, and ſhe ſeem'd to be ſo full of Confuſion, that the trouble that I had occaſion'd to her, gave me a new Vexation. The Habit they had brought me was handſom, and ſet me off to the beſt advantage: I had a great deal of Love, Fear, and Reſpect. This was a happy moment for me, and <hi>Thamirize</hi> granted to my ardent Supplications a Pardon, without which it was impoſſible for me to live; and though ſhe did not Treat me as ſhe had done <hi>Irmiſe,</hi> I was nevertheleſs well ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>They who ſaw me abide in <hi>Kachen,</hi> and were of the party of my Rivals, believed that really the Princeſs had had a hand in my Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſe. But <hi>Othrize</hi> and <hi>Benzide</hi> openly decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red themſelves my Enemies, and publickly ſwore my Ruine. They had ſeen me defend my Life ſo well that they had no mind to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tack me without advantage. In the end, my Lord, their Factions were ſo powerful, and their Parties grew furious to that height, as to pretend to force the Princeſs to make a Choice. It was to no purpoſe to repreſent that the Royal Authority was encroach'd upon in <hi>Philing</hi>'s abſence; her Words were too weak a Bridle to reſtrain ſo ungovernable boldneſs, and the two Princes agreed, that for whom
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:55009:88"/>
                  <hi>Thamirize</hi> ſhould declare, ſhould remain peaceable Maſter of her Perſon and Kingdom. She reſiſted a great while; but what could ſhe do in a general Revolt? I offer'd to dye in her Service; and when you are dead, ſaid ſhe unto me, Shall I be leſs unhappy. Well, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, ſaid I, I believe an Advice which you may perhaps judge intereſted, but is nevertheleſs very ſincere. Intruſt your ſelf to my Reſpect; let us depart from <hi>Thibet:</hi> let us go into <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,</hi> where the King your Brother will have doubtleſs found <hi>Axione;</hi> and after we have put you in a ſecure Place, it will be caſie for us to come and puniſh your unworthy Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects. <hi>Thamirize</hi> ſtarted a thouſand Difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which my Reaſons ſurmounted; and in ſpite of the great number of Spies that watch'd over her, I look ſo juſt and happy meaſures, that we eſcap'd out of <hi>Kachen</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any trouble, and afterwards got out of <hi>Thibet,</hi> bringing along with us only one of the Princeſſe's Maids, and twenty Men for a Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy. By diligent Pains, and different Paths we enter'd into <hi>Tartary;</hi> the Princeſs bore with courage the Fatigues of a long Journey, and Yeſterday in the Evening we arrived at <hi>Cambalu,</hi> where hearing of the Tragedy that was like to be acted, I immediately determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to expoſe my Life for that of <hi>Zingis.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, my Lord, ſaid <hi>Omir</hi> to <hi>Philing,</hi> I have told you my Crime, and the ſtate in which we left <hi>Whibet.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="172" facs="tcp:55009:89"/>
               <p>The Brother of <hi>Thamarize</hi> did tenderly embrace her Lover, &amp; thank'd him in expreſſions full of gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude for what he had done for her: The Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions in <hi>Thibet</hi> did not much diſquiet him, being perſwaded that <hi>Benzide</hi> and <hi>Othrize</hi> whom he knew, would deſtroy one another.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Omir</hi> charm'd with his happineſs taſted perfect joy at the feet of <hi>Thamarize,</hi> who now ſuffer'd without Conſtraint and Affection to appear that was autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riz'd by the King her Brother. All <hi>Zingis</hi>'s thoughts run upon <hi>Taxila,</hi> and <hi>Philing</hi> ſtill in vain ſolicited the obſtinate <hi>Axione</hi> to make him happy.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> recover'd from his Fury, look'd upon the Death of <hi>Zamar</hi> and that of <hi>Timur,</hi> as Effects of the Juſtice of Heaven: Finding himſelf then freed from the Empire of the proud Queen, he repented of his Weakneſs, and renouncing theſe Grandeurs which had only ſerv'd to enable him to execute his Injuſtice; his only deſire was to abandon them to <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Taxila,</hi> for whom he was then ſenſible of a true Tenderneſs.</p>
               <p>Whilſt the three ſatisfied Lovers entertain'd the three faireſt Perſons of the World, with what they felt for them; the careful <hi>Almundzar</hi> was razing <hi>Zamar</hi> out of the remembrance of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan,</hi> by Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes full of Vertue.</p>
               <p>The King of <hi>Tartary</hi> order'd Preparations to be made with a Royal Magnificence for the Solemnity of the Marriage of <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Taxila,</hi> and the Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remony of their Coronation. Six Diadems were in one day added to the Crown, and the Valour of <hi>Zin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis</hi> promis'd a great many others. <hi>Almundzar</hi> was agreeably occupi'd with theſe Cares; and one Day as he was in the Place before the Palace, where he was cauſing to erect a ſplendid Triumphal Arch, in lieu of the unworthy Scaffold, that a little before
<pb n="173" facs="tcp:55009:89"/>was to be ſeen in that Place; he was accoſted by a Man, whoſe Meen ſurpriz'd him. He was Old but Venerable. My Lord, ſaid he unto him, Since all the Power here is in your Hands, it is to you that I addreſs my ſelf, to obtain for me a moments Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the King of the <hi>Mogols,</hi> to whom I muſt impart matters of very great Importance. <hi>Almund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zar</hi> full of Zeal for all that concern'd <hi>Zingis,</hi> car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried the old Stranger without delay to <hi>Taxila</hi>'s Chamber, where the King of the <hi>Mogols</hi> was with <hi>Philing, Omir, Thamarize,</hi> and <hi>Axione.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As ſoon as the old Man had caſt his Eyes upon the laſt of them, he appear'd Planet-ſtruck: Great Gods, cry'd he out, tranſported with Joy! it is then true that you reſtore unto me that Princeſs whom I loſt in <hi>Thibet.</hi> O <hi>Axione!</hi> O <hi>Zenelie!</hi> Who would have ſaid that ever I ſhould ſee you again?</p>
               <p>His Exclamation ſurpriz'd this Illuſtrious Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: But the Stranger continued thus, and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſing himſelf to <hi>Zingis;</hi> My Lord, ſaid he unto him, This fair <hi>Axione,</hi> whom you behold, is the Princeſs <hi>Zenelie</hi> your Siſter, who was taken away violently from the Queen your Mother, by a Troop of Robbers of the <hi>Tartarian</hi> Mountaineers, in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Voyage that ſhe made: But I muſt demonſtrate this Truth unto you in a more orderly method.</p>
               <p>I am a <hi>Mogol,</hi> my Lord, born a Subject to the King your Father, and ſerv'd the Queen in one of the principal Charges of the Houſe: I follow'd her in the Voyage I ſpoke of, which the languiſhing Condition of her Health oblig'd her to undertake. She would carry the young Princeſs along with her, for ſhe could not endure to be ſeparated from her: in traverſing a Foreſt, theſe cruel Men, in number much ſurpaſſing us, forc'd us to yield to them, and took <hi>Zenelie</hi> away with them, whom they were eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:55009:90"/>able to carry off. The Queen was over-whelm'd with Grief, and I with ſeveral great Wounds: I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wail'd her Misfortunes, and upbraided my ſelf with Weakneſs. As ſoon as I was cur'd, I made a Vow to take no reſt till I had found <hi>Zenelie;</hi> and leaving the afflicted Queen, I viſited all the Places where I believ'd I might hear News of the Raviſhers of <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie.</hi> More than two years paſt over in this manner, and I was inform'd by Fame of the Death of the Queen of the <hi>Mogols:</hi> I wander'd about ſtill, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving no Family at <hi>Molg,</hi> and one Day, more happy than the reſt, I rencounter'd in <hi>Thibet</hi> the Captain of theſe Robbers that had carried away <hi>Zenelie,</hi> and that Princeſs her ſelf with him. I eaſily knew her; but ſhe did not retain any Idea of me. I ask'd that Robber what he pretended to do with a Child that was none of his. He anſwer'd me with Diſdain, and ſeveral times call'd her <hi>Axione.</hi> Wearied with ſpeaking to him in vain, being then as well accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied as himſelf, I fought him, and we reduc'd one another into ſuch a condition, that <hi>Axione</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone remain'd ſtanding. Se was then in the ſeventh year of her Age. There arrived a great many per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons on Horſe-back, who in all probability carried away <hi>Axione</hi> or <hi>Zenelie.</hi> For me, I loſt my Senſes, and lay long in that condition: but ſome men that liv'd in the bottom of the Foreſt, where they kept ſome Flocks, came to the place where I was, and finding me yet warm, carried me to their Cave. I was there more than ſix Months before I could ſtand upright; having only the advantage of ſome Sim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples for my Cure. I was even conſtrain'd for want of Strength, to live many years in that Deſart: I Inſenſibly accuſtom'd my ſelf to it. But when Time hadre-eſtabliſh'd me in better Health, I forſook the Foreſt, in which my Weakneſs had buried me ſo
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:55009:90"/>long. I ſearch'd, I run through a thouſand places; but at length, hearing that there was at <hi>Cambalu</hi> an unknown Maid call'd <hi>Axione,</hi> I came hither, I have ſeen her, and I find that ſhe is <hi>Zenelie,</hi> ſo like the Queen her Mother, that one cannot obſerve the leaſt difference between them. Then <hi>Metaphanes</hi> ſhew'd them a Picture of the Queen of the <hi>Mogols,</hi> which he had ſtill preſerv'd; and although it had been done for <hi>Axione,</hi> it could not have reſembl'd her more perfectly. All the Circumſtances of her For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune correſponding exactly with that of <hi>Zenelie,</hi> no body doubted but that ſhe was the Princeſs of the <hi>Mogols. Zingis</hi> embrac'd a thouſand times this ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Siſter, who return'd his Careſſes with tender<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>Taxila</hi> and <hi>Thamirize</hi> teſtified their ſenſible Joy to <hi>Zenelie</hi> by all that could expreſs it; and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> tranſported, threw himſelf at her Feet. <hi>Zingis</hi> aſſur'd him that ſhe was his, and the young Princeſs did not contradict this Illuſtrious Brother.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> was inform'd of this Diſcovery, and <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphanes</hi> told him the particulars thereof. In the end, Joy reſounded over all the Palace, and the wiſh'd for time that was to unite theſe ſix perſons, was come.</p>
               <p>That great Day was pompouſly ſolemniz'd: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo much Splendor and Riches appear'd at one time. The Temple where the Ceremony of the Marriage was to be perform'd, was crouded with an infinite number of <hi>Tartars</hi> and Strangers. <hi>Philing</hi> and <hi>Omir</hi> bore up the Mantle-Royal of <hi>Zingis,</hi> and <hi>Zenelie</hi> and <hi>Thamirize</hi> that of <hi>Taxila.</hi> The Scepters and Crowns were plac'd on a magnificent Throne, and after theſe happy Lovers were united together in an eternal Bond, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> with his own Hand Crown'd <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Taxila.</hi> Afterwards the new Emperour Crown'd <hi>Philing</hi> and <hi>Omir,</hi> and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:55009:91"/>
                  <hi>Taxila</hi> perform'd the ſame Honour to <hi>Ze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelie</hi> and <hi>Thamarize.</hi> The People without ceaſing repeated the Names of <hi>Zingis</hi> and <hi>Taxila,</hi> and Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ended the famous Day. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> would no longer undertake the Charge, or retain any marks of his Dignity, leaving all in the hands of perſons that ſo juſtly deſerved theſe Honours. Not long after they were inform'd, as <hi>Philing</hi> had foretold, that <hi>Benzide</hi> and <hi>Othrize</hi> had periſh'd in their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, and Ambaſſadors from <hi>Thibet</hi> came to aſſure <hi>Philing</hi> that his Sublects remain'd conſtant in their Allegiance to him: He ſtay'd in <hi>Tartary</hi> at <hi>Zingis</hi>'s deſire; as did alſo <hi>Omir</hi> with the Title of King of <hi>Brema. Zingis</hi> enlarg'd very much the Limits of <hi>Thibet,</hi> and teſtified by his Liberality to the Princeſs his Siſter, how dear ſhe was unto him. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndkan</hi> dy'd not long after, and was lamented, for the laſt of his Actions had aboliſh'd the Remembrance of the reſt. In fine, <hi>Zingis</hi> founded the moſt puiſſant Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in <hi>Aſia,</hi> and render'd his Name ſo Famous, that all the Univerſe was fill'd with it: He ſubdued <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, Perſia,</hi> and all that is between the <hi>Tigris</hi> and <hi>Volga. Philing</hi> and <hi>Omir</hi> ſhared in his Glory, and follow'd him in his happy Expeditions. <hi>Almundzar</hi> was conſider'd according to his Deſert. <hi>Metaphanes</hi> dy'd for Joy, having ſeen <hi>Zenelie</hi> Queen of <hi>Thibet. Zerbin</hi> receiv'd the Recompences due unto his Fide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, and theſe Princes full of Days and Honour, left behind them a numerous and glorious Poſterity.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>THere is lately Printed, <hi>A Preſent for the Ladies;</hi> being an Hiſtorical Vindication of the <hi>Female Sex:</hi> By <hi>N. Tate.</hi> To which is added, The <hi>Character</hi> of an <hi>Accompliſh'd Virgin, Wife,</hi> and <hi>Widow;</hi> In Verſe.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:55009:91"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
